<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sober discourse of right to church-communion wherein is proved by Scripture, the example of the primitive times, and the practice of all that have prosessed the Christian religion, that no unbaptized person may be regularly admitted to the Lords Supper / by W. Kiffin ...</title>
            <author>Kiffin, William, 1616-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K425</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10604</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12425209</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12425209</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61819</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61819)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 944:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sober discourse of right to church-communion wherein is proved by Scripture, the example of the primitive times, and the practice of all that have prosessed the Christian religion, that no unbaptized person may be regularly admitted to the Lords Supper / by W. Kiffin ...</title>
                  <author>Kiffin, William, 1616-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28], 131 [i.e. 163] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Geo. Larkin for Enoch Prosser ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [12]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61819:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61819:1"/>
            <p>A Sober Diſcourſe OF RIGHT TO <hi>Church-Communion.</hi>
Wherein is proved by <hi>Scripture,</hi> the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the <hi>Primitive</hi>
Times, and the Practice of All that have Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the <hi>Chriſtian
Religion:</hi> That no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbaptized</hi> perſon may be
<hi>Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly</hi> admitted to the <hi>Lords Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W. Kiffin</hi> a lover of Truth and Peace</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Act. 2.41.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>Then they that gladly received his Word were Baptized: and the
ſame day there were added to them about three thouſand Souls.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Deut. 5.32.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye ſhall obſerve to do therefore as the Lord your God hath
Commanded you, you ſhal not turn aſide to the right hand or to the
left.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Col. 2.5.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>Joying and beholding your order and the ſtedfaſtneſs of
your Faith in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Geo. Larkin,</hi> for <hi>Enoch
Proſſer,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in
<hi>Sweethings-Alley,</hi> at the Eaſt End of the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi>
1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:61819:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61819:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>WHen it pleaſed <hi>God</hi> of his <hi>free</hi> Grace to
cauſe me to make a ſerious <hi>inquiry</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Jeſus
Chriſt,</hi> and to give me ſome taſt of his pardoning <hi>Love,</hi> the
ſence of which did ingage my heart with deſires to be obedient to his will
in <hi>all</hi> things. I uſed all indeavers both by Converſe with ſuch
as were able, and alſo by diligently ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, with
earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of God, that I might be directed in a right <hi>way</hi>
of Worſhip; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome time concluded that the ſafeſt way was to
follow the <hi>Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of the Flock</hi> (namely) that <hi>Order</hi> laid
down by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and Practiſed by the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive 
<pb facs="tcp:61819:3"/>Chriſtians in their times, which I found to be; that after
Converſion they were <hi>Baptiſed, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> to the Church, and
<hi>Continued in the Apoſtles Doctrine, Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Breaking of Bread, and
Prayer;</hi> according to which I thought my ſelf bound to be Conformable,
and having continued in the Profeſſion of the ſame for theſe forty
years, although through many <hi>Weakneſſes,</hi> and <hi>Fears,
Temptations,</hi> and <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,</hi> yet not without ſome
<hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> from God of his gracious <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance</hi> and Strength
to this very day: The ſence I have of my own Weakneſs and Inability, would
have been a Bar to me to appear in this Publick way, did I not ſee a
<hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> lying upon me for the Truths-ſake, and the ſakes of
many, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome that have lately riſen up to weaken, if not make
void that great Ordinance of Baptiſm, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to maintain, that all
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that Believe, although they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<pb facs="tcp:61819:3"/>did, nor do Practice
the ſame, may partake of the Ordinance of the Lords Supper, and all other
Goſpel inſtituted Duties. <hi>A Notion,</hi> not only <hi>Contrary</hi> to
the <hi>Primitive</hi> Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, but the <hi>Conſtant</hi> Practice of all
that ever profeſſed the Chriſtian Religion, or that own the Scriptures to
be the Rule of Faith and Practiſe; and it would be a happineſs to the
Chriſtian Religion, if all that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the ſame, did in other things
agree as they do in this, namely, that none ought to be Partakers of the Lords
Supper, but ſuch as have been Baptiſed thoſe that differ; in this matter
from them, would be found to be as <hi>few</hi> in Number as they are
<hi>Weak</hi> in Argument, and although I am well ſatisfied that the
performance of all Duties and Ordinances, will be of no value to any man,
further than Chriſt is injoyed in them: the very Goſpel it ſelf
<hi>Severed</hi> from Chriſt, will prove the <hi>Adminiſtration of Death, 2
Cor. 1.21.</hi> The Power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuleſt<pb facs="tcp:61819:4"/>
               <hi>Preaching,</hi> and the
cleareſt Diſcourſe of the free Grace of God hath <hi>no Life</hi> in it,
unleſs the ſoul be led by the Spirit to Chriſt, who is the Life of all
Duties. Knowledge of the Truth, and Obedience to it in outward performances,
will as little ſave a mans ſoul as the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works. Yet every man
that hath an intereſt in Chriſt, is bound by the Word of God to be obedient
to all his Commands. It was the great Commendation of <hi>Zacharias</hi> and
<hi>Elizabeth, That they walked in all the Commandments and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the
Lord blameleſs,</hi> the Ordinance of Baptiſm is none of the leaſt, the
very Foundation of Religion being comprehended in the Form thereof, as
appeareth at large by the Worthy and Learned Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> in his Book of
the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature and Perſonality of the Holy Spirit, <hi>pag. 50.</hi> viz.
<hi>All things neceſſary to this purpoſe, are compriſed in the ſolemn
form<pb facs="tcp:61819:4"/>of our Initiation into Covenant with God,</hi> Matth. 28.19.
<hi>Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt Commands his Apoſtles to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple all
Nations, Baptiſing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and the
Holy Ghoſt, this is the Foundation we lay of our Obedience and
Profeſſion, which are to be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by this Initial ingagement</hi> pag.
51. <hi>No ſence can be afixed unto theſe words but what doth unavoidably
include his Perſonality, we are alike Baptiſed into their Name, equally
ſubmiting to their Authority, and equally taking the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their
Name upon us.</hi> Again, <hi>By being Baptiſed into the Name of the</hi>
Father, <hi>and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, we are Sacredly Initiated,
and Conſecrated, or Dedicated unto the Service and Worſhip of the Father,
Son, and Holy Ghoſt; this we take upon us in our Baptiſm: herein lies the
Foundation of all our Faith and Profeſſion with that ingagement of our
ſelves unto God, which Conſtitutes our Chriſtianity; this is the pledge
of our entrance into Covenant with God, and of our giving up our ſelves unto
him in the ſolemn Bond of Religion.</hi> And concludes in pag. 52. <hi>If the
Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine<pb facs="tcp:61819:5"/>of a Trinity of Perſons ſubſiſting in the ſame
undivided Eſſence, be not taught and declar in theſe words, we may
juſtly deſpair of ever having any Divine Myſtery manifeſted unto us, I
leave the Reader to peruſe it at large.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this Ordinance of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> be the Pledge of our
Entrance into Covenant with God, and of the giving up our ſelves unto him in
the ſolemn Bond of Religion, and we are hereby Dedicated unto the ſervice
of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, then muſt it of neceſſity be the
<hi>Firſt</hi> Ordinance, before that of the Lords Supper. We may as well
conclude a man may go into a Houſe before he Enters, and a man may be paid
for his Goods, and afterwards receive Earneſt, as any may lawfully partake of
the Lords Supper be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is Baptized. And if we are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credly Initiated
and Conſecrated, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated unto the Worſhip of the Father, Son, and
Holy Ghoſt, as that Text <hi>Matth. 28,19.</hi> ſheweth we are, and take
this upon us in our Baptiſm, and thereby owning the Spirit to be God, equal
with the Father, and the Son, as that Faith which is to be exerciſed by us in
all other Ordinances, than the admit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of perſons<pb facs="tcp:61819:5"/>to the Lords <hi>Supper,</hi> and other
Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Duties, before they are <hi>Baptiſed,</hi> doth greatly weaken
this <hi>main</hi> Argument of the <hi>Spirits being God,</hi> at leaſt in
the Practice of theſe Goſpel Duties, for from what Scripture will it be
made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that he is ſo to be owned in them, if ye partake of them
before, or without being Baptiſed? if this be laid as the Foundation of all
our Faith, and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which are to be built upon in all our
Profeſſion, if it be omited, the ſtructure muſt needs be weak, we had
need rather to have our Faith ſtrengthened in the belief of ſo great and
eſſential a Truth as the Divine Eſſence of the Spirit is, by the uſe
of all means appointed to that end.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Francis Cheynel</hi> in his Learned Treatiſe, of the
<hi>Divine Trinity,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1650. <hi>pag. 258.</hi> quotes it as the
Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Iraeneus, Tertullian, Athanaſius, Baſil,</hi> and others
of the Ancients, That the <hi>Principal</hi> Fundamentals of the
<hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith</hi> is Contained in the Form of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and
founded on <hi>Matt. 28.19.</hi> And in <hi>page 185.</hi> tells us, <hi>If any
man in</hi> Athanaſius<hi>'s time asked, how many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Subſiſt in
the Godhead, they were wont to ſend him to</hi> Jordan, <hi>and there you may
hear and ſee the bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:61819:6"/>Matt. 3.16. <hi>in
pag. 381. God the Holy Ghoſt is to be obey'd, we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to his Service
in Baptiſm. And</hi> pag. 430. <hi>In Baptiſm we Chriſtians are devoted
and Conſecrated to the Belief, Worſhip, and Service of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God
the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> By which we may ſee, what Eſteem
the Antients had of that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and great Reaſon there is for every
Chriſtian to be found in the Practice thereof, ſeeing they are thereby
Baptized into Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, as the <hi>firſt</hi> Foundation
of our <hi>viſible</hi> Profeſſion of Chriſt; for as
<hi>Repentance</hi> is the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>initiating</hi> grace; ſo Baptiſm
is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Baptiſm of Repentance as the firſt <hi>initiating</hi>
Ordinance.</p>
            <p>I have for the ſatisfaction of <hi>All,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured in the
following Eſſay to clear this truth both from <hi>Scripture</hi> and
<hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,</hi> as alſo to produce the Judgment of the <hi>Learned</hi> in
all Ages. As for our Modern Divines, you have their own words ſet down
faithfully by me, and as for thoſe who are more Ancient, I have requeſted a
Friend to Tranſlate the ſame, which I doubt not but is done Impartially.
And although I may expect to meet with Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures from ſome who will be
ready to charge<pb facs="tcp:61819:6"/>the Truth herein with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs and to be
of a dividing Nature; yet I can with comfort and ſincerity of heart in the
Preſence of <hi>God</hi> declare, I have no other deſign, but the
preſerving the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt, in their purity and Order as they are
left unto us in the holy <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> of Truth; and to warn the
Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <hi>To keep cloſe to the Rule,</hi> leaſt they being found not to
Worſhip the Lord according to his preſcrib'd Order he make a
<hi>Breach</hi> amongſt them, neither are you preſented with any new
Opinion, but that which hath been the Judgment of all that have Profeſſed
the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> in all times; ſo that what Cenſure any
ſhall make upon it, reſpects not us only, but the ſervants of God of all
Perſwaſions in all Ages, and for my ſelf, as I have a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in my
own Conſcience, ſo I doubt not but I have the ſame alſo with thoſe
that know me, that I have made it a great part of my Duty, as I have had
opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to perſuade all Chriſtians to <hi>Love</hi> and
<hi>Peace,</hi> to avoid judging, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching each other under their
differing Perſwaſions, to turn their Heats and Paſſions, which hath
greatly abounded in our days one againſt another, into Prayer, and
Supplication <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for another, 
<pb facs="tcp:61819:7"/>that although they differ in their Light, it may not make any
breach in their Love; He that knows moſt of the mind of God, knows but in
part, for who art thou that judgeſt another mans ſervant? I ſhall trouble
you no farther, but leave the peruſal of this ſmall Eſſay to thy
ſerious conſideration.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Service of Chriſt, <hi>W.
K.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 7. <hi>line</hi> 23. read <hi>Waldenſes.</hi> p. 13.
margent for <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra</hi> r. <hi>fruſtra,</hi> p. 18. <hi>l.</hi> 8. r.
<hi>practiſers.</hi> p. 35. <hi>l.</hi> 20. r. <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed.</hi> p.
47. <hi>l.</hi> 19. dele <hi>of.</hi> l. 24. for <hi>at</hi> r. <hi>until.</hi>
p. 57. <hi>l.</hi> 5. r. <hi>The Rule.</hi> p. 70. <hi>l.</hi> 11. r.
<hi>principles.</hi> p. 75. margent <hi>l.</hi> 4. r. <hi>that they.</hi> p.
83. <hi>l.</hi> 14. r. <hi>Suſpiciens.</hi> p. 85. <hi>l.</hi> 15. r.
<hi>Catechumens.</hi> p, 86. <hi>l.</hi> 11. r. <hi>Yet the. l.</hi> 23. r.
<hi>except.</hi> p. 89. r. <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> for p. 89. r. 87. for 92. r. 90.
for 93. r. 91. for 96. r. 94. for 97. r. 95. where line 9. r. <hi>But. l.</hi>
11. r. <hi>Baptizing.</hi> p. 97. <hi>l.</hi> 11. r. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itiation.</hi> p.
108. <hi>l.</hi> 1. r. <hi>Judgment.</hi> p. 109. <hi>l.</hi> 23. r. <hi>of
Chriſt Commonly.</hi> p. 110. <hi>l.</hi> 18. r. <hi>conſequence.</hi> for
p. 211. r. 112. where <hi>l.</hi> 24. r. <hi>to joy in beholding.</hi> laſt
<hi>l.</hi> r. <hi>none.</hi> p. 118. <hi>l.</hi> 16. dele <hi>others,</hi> p.
132. <hi>l.</hi> 11. for <hi>firſt</hi> r. <hi>later.</hi> p. 136.
<hi>l.</hi> 19. dele <hi>to</hi> p. 140. <hi>l.</hi> 21. r. <hi>choice of.
l.</hi> 22. r. <hi>inforce.</hi> p. 148. <hi>l.</hi> 10 for <hi>ſheet</hi> r.
<hi>ſtreet.</hi> p. 153. <hi>l.</hi> 12. r. <hi>by the.</hi> p. 158. margent
<hi>l.</hi> 9. dele <hi>one Law.</hi> p. 144. laſt <hi>l.</hi> for
<hi>But</hi> r. <hi>By.</hi> Litteral eſcapes and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointings are left to
the Candor of the Reader, to Correct or Pardon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:61819:7"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>WHat was Praiſe-worthy in thoſe Primitive
<hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> to whom the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> writes, 1.
<hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. Can be no Blemiſh, but really a Duty in other
Chriſtians, in after times, to imitate; his words are, <hi>I praiſe you,
Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that ye remember me in all things, and keep the Ordinances as</hi> I
<hi>delivered them to you:</hi> our Tranſlation of the 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>Greek Word (rendring it <hi>Ordinances</hi>) is excepted
againſt by ſome Papiſts, eſpecially <hi>Gregory<pb facs="tcp:61819:8"/>Martin,</hi>
reputed a great Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſt in the <hi>Rhemiſh</hi> Seminary, who would have
it Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (<hi>Traditions</hi>) to countenance the <hi>Romiſh</hi>
Opinion; to which ſhall be oppoſed that the Greek Word ſignifies indeed
<hi>Tradition,</hi> that is in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> a <hi>Delivery, viz.</hi> of
<hi>Doctrines, Ordinances, Inſtructions,</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions,</hi> 2.
<hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.15. by thoſe Evangelical Preachers to their Auditors,
which is nothing elſe but the Doctrine of the Goſpel firſt Preached,
(which is of the greateſt and higheſt Authority,) and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards committed
to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles, as ſtanding Records to
future Ages; ſo that any<pb facs="tcp:61819:8"/>
               <hi>Traditions,</hi> beſides what is
written, are juſtly to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt, and (in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters relating to
Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) to be eſteem'd Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal. Becauſe a Delivery of
Tranſactions or Doctrines by Anceſtors to Poſterity by word of Mouth, is
liable to many miſtakes and uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by reaſon of the different
conſtitutions and circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men, who frequently introduce that
Authority to colour their Inventions, or the product of their imaginary
Fancies, with reſpect to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Matters. Though it is very apparent that
ſuch a Rule is not at all <hi>ſelf-evidencing,</hi> for it cannot prove it
ſelf; nor<pb facs="tcp:61819:9"/>is it <hi>Demonſtrative,</hi> for it has no certain
<hi>Medium</hi> to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince; nor Univerſally <hi>True</hi> in all times and
places, becauſe Reports vary every where; neither is it Unerring, being no
where ſtampt with that Character; and laſtly not Plain, for no doubting
perſon can poſſibly examine all Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. Now theſe are ſome of
the properties of a General Rule to try Controverſies by, which being wanting
in <hi>Oral Traditions,</hi> the <hi>word</hi> cannot here be underſtood
otherwiſe than by <hi>Ordinances</hi> or <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> of the
Goſpel 
<note n="*" place="margin">So the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ack, Verſion,</hi> &amp; <hi>Vatablus,</hi> render
it.</note> Recorded in the Scriptures, which were given for our Inſtruction,
2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. written by the immediate <pb facs="tcp:61819:9"/>Dictates of the
Spirit; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the gracious Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God in the Church, from the
injuries of Time, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and Fraud, through all Ages; they have been kept
with much greater care, than any other Books, Tranſlated into all Languages,
retained both by Orthodox and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, diligently obſerving and watching
each other, ſo that there could not poſſibly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en any remarkable
variation or alteration in them, but that preſently the whole world would
have exclaimed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p>Mans Nature is very prone to be medling with things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his
Commiſſion, which<pb facs="tcp:61819:10"/>has prov'd the very peſt and bane of
Chriſtianity; for not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that dreadful prohibition, <hi>Rev.</hi>
22.18,19. of <hi>adding to,</hi> or <hi>taking from</hi> his word, is not
<hi>Europe</hi> full of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Additions and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions in the
Worſhip of God, which are impoſed as Magiſterially as if enſtampt with
a Divine Character, though in themſelves no other than (as Chriſt himſelf
calls them) <hi>the Traditions of men! Matth.</hi> 15.3. It is a ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
and deſperate piece of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacity for men to preſume to mend any thing in
the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God; for it ſuppoſes the All-wiſe Law giver capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of
error, and the attempter<pb facs="tcp:61819:10"/>wiſer than his Maker. And if Soveraign
Princes and Worldly States be ſo jealous of their Prerogatives and
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Rights, that they will (to the utmoſt hazard) repel any
Invader: If men be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed to have their Laws undervalued by the
private Judgments of thoſe who ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Interpret than obey them: 
<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Rom. Hom. 2.</note>If the
Conqueſt of an Enemy againſt the Command of his General, coſt a
<hi>Roman</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man his life, though his own Father were the Judge: 
<note place="margin">Briſton, de Reg. Perſ. lib. 1.</note>If the
killing of a Lion contrary to the Laws of the Kings Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (though to
reſcue the King himſelf) coſt a poor <hi>Perſian</hi> his Head: If the
Architect that <pb facs="tcp:61819:11"/>brought not the ſame (but as he judged a fitter)
piece of Timber than he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, to a <hi>Roman</hi> Conſul, was
rewarded with a bundle of Rods. If 
<note n="*" place="margin">Levit. 10.1,2.</note>
               <hi>Nadab</hi> and
<hi>Abihu</hi> came to a Tragical end for their prohibited ſervice, in
offering not the <hi>ſame</hi> that was <hi>commanded,</hi> but <hi>ſtrange
fire</hi> before the Lord; what ſhall we ſay to ſuch as mix their
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions with the Sacred In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions and Preſcripts of the Great
unerring Soveraign? When the ſame perſon who is to perform the Obedience,
ſhall dare to appoint the Laws? Implying a perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry purpoſe of no
further ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance than may conſiſt<pb facs="tcp:61819:11"/>with the allowance of
his own Judgment? Whereas true Obedience muſt be grounded on the Majeſty of
that Power that Commands, not on the Judgment of the Subject, or benefit of the
Preſcript propoſed; not ſo much from the Quality of the things Commanded,
as from the Authority of him that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes. Is not ſuch a Practice an
Invaſion upon Chriſts Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative? Do not ſuch men make themſelves (as
it were) Joynt Authors of his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances? And may it not be truly ſaid that
whoever Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices any Inſtitution other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than as was appointed by the
Supreme Law-giver,<pb facs="tcp:61819:12"/>
               <hi>does not Honour the Ordinance, but an Idol
of his own making? Mixtures</hi> are uſeful for two purpoſes; <hi>viz.</hi>
Either to ſlaken and abate ſome thing that is <hi>exceſſive,</hi> or to
ſupply ſomething that is <hi>deficient:</hi> and ſo all
<hi>Heterogeneous</hi> mixtures do plainly intimate, either a Viciouſneſs
to be Corrected, or a Defect to be Supplyed. Now it is no leſs than
<hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> to charge either of theſe upon the Pure and Perfect
Word of God, and any Gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that take away or diminiſh the force of it,
or human Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions that argue any defect, are equally dangerous and impious.
To ſtamp any thing of a humane Original with a<pb facs="tcp:61819:12"/>Divine Character,
and father it upon God, is one of the higheſt and moſt daring
Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions the Pride of man can aſpire unto, and is provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt
by ſpecial prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions and threatning, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.32. and 18.20.
<hi>Jer.</hi> 26.2. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.6.</p>
            <p>When that queſtion ſhall be askt, <hi>Who hath required this
at your hands?</hi> I doubt it will be no ſufficient plea to ſay, That if
we have erred in any Punctilio's of Divine Truth, it was for Peace and Unions
ſake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For, <hi>No motions of Peace are to be made or
received with the loſs of Truth:</hi> Nor may the Laws, Orders, and
Preſcriptions of Chriſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered,<pb facs="tcp:61819:13"/>or varyed, in any tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
upon any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, God having never given any ſuch Prerogative
to mankind, as to be Arbitrators how he may be beſt and moſt decently
Worſhiped.</p>
            <p>It is not to be queſtioned but all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> or
any ſober impartial Perſons, that bear any Reverence to the Divine
Majeſty and his holy Word, will readily own theſe Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<hi>Theories,</hi> which are ſo ſelf-evidencing, that if any gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay
them, he does at the ſame time ſtrike at the Majeſty, Wiſdom, and
Authority of GOD, the moſt daring and deſperate Enterprize in the
World.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:61819:13"/>Now this being (as it muſt be) granted,
<hi>viz.</hi> That no part of Gods Law, or Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, whether we reſpect the
<hi>Manner</hi> or <hi>Form,</hi> or the <hi>Matter</hi> and
<hi>Subſtance</hi> thereof, is to be altered without the expreſs Order and
Direction of GOD Himſelf; It will lead us to a Sober Enquiry, <hi>Whether the
Opinion here examined, be grounded upon the Law and Word of God.</hi> To do
which, for Methods ſake, 
<list>
                  <item>Chap. 1. <hi>We will ſtate the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Chap. 2. <hi>We will propoſe ſome Reaſons why
Unbaptiſed Perſons may not be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Lords Supper.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:61819:14"/>Chap. 3. <hi>We will produce ſome Scripture-Demonſtrations to evidence that ſuch a Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> (viz. <hi>ſo to
admit them</hi>) <hi>is not Evangelical.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Chap. 4. <hi>We will ſhew that it is againſt the
Practice and Judgment of all Chriſtians that have owned Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for
above Sixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Chap. 5. <hi>We will Anſwer Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of which Heads, we ſhall labour to ſift
out Truth <hi>Impartially,</hi> propoſe our own Judgment candidly and
plainly, without the leaſt Reflection upon, or Prejudice to our Chriſtian
Brethren that<pb facs="tcp:61819:14"/>diſſent from us in this Point, with whom and with
all that can own the Name of the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> according to his
Goſpel, we deſire to live in Brotherly Love and Chriſtian Society, and if
we find our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren entertain any unſound Notion with reſpect to
<hi>Goſpel Truths,</hi> we look upon it as our duty to endeavour to inform
them of it, in a meek and ſober way; and if we fail of ſucceſs, then to
leave them to the Lord, who in his own due Seaſon will uncloud thoſe Sacred
My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, which yet are hidden to a great many.</p>
            <p>We are not willing to be Cenſorious, nor arrogate that wiſdom
to our ſelves, as to<pb facs="tcp:61819:15"/>think that we are wiſer than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet
in all Modeſty we may be bold to affirm, <hi>that in the point here handled,
we have the Scriptures, and the concurrence of 
<note n="*" place="margin">See Ch. 4. follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> all
Chriſtians from the beginning, to this Age, on our ſide;</hi> whereas the
oppoſite Opinion can cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge but a few Favourites, and is of a very late
Original: which is not the main Reaſon brought here to oppoſe it, but only
ſerves for a Collateral E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, to illuſtrate the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments propoſed
from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to ſhew that the eminent Profeſſors of, and
Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers for Chriſtianity have owned it, which is no ſlight
Circumſtance to ſober and conſidering Chriſtians.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61819:15"/>A Sober Diſcourſe of Right to
Church-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: Wherein is proved, That no Unbaptized Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may be
Regularly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
         </head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. I. The Queſtion Stated.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Stating of this Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it may be neceſſary to
examine how far we diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we concur with our Diſſenting
Brethren, becauſe that will prevent much needleſs Diſcourſe, and lead
us to debate the matter in Diſpute on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:61819:16"/>The Profeſſors of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion,
are diſtinguiſhed by certain terms, invented by their oppoſites, to know
them by, as <hi>Prelatical, Presbyterian, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, Anabaptiſt,</hi>
&amp;c. And it were well if ſuch names were laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and the Title of
Chriſtian Brother reaſſumed, becauſe they agree in Fundamentals. Now of
all theſe, our Controverſie in the Caſe in hand is only with ſome on
the laſt, who are (though not rightly) called <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> As for
the others, their avowed Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple is, To admit none into Church-Fellowſhip
or Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that are Unbaptized: Yea ſo poſitive are the Papiſts, that
they look upon all ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing qualified for Church Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnnion, till
they are Baptized, that they ſay they are all damn'd that die without it; but
we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive no Authority from their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. the Church of <hi>England</hi> 
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61819:16"/>receives no Member into their Communion without Baptiſm,
neither do <hi>Presbyterians, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants,</hi> nor indeed any ſort of
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians that own Ordinances, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any as a Church-Member without
Baptiſm. We ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore direct this Diſcourſe to our
Diſſenting Brethren, of the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized way only, who reaſon thus, <hi>That
there being no Precept, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident nor Example in all the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, for our
excluding our Holy Brethren that differ in this Point from us, therefore we
ought not to dare to do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now how unſafe, unſound, and of what pernicious Conſequence,
ſuch a Poſition in its direct ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency is and has been, ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in
the Chapter of Objections; to which at preſent we refer—Only in general
we ſay, That if by <hi>Precept, Preſident,</hi> or <hi>Example,</hi> is
meant ſuch, in <hi>expreſs</hi> words, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch Texts of
Scripture as<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61819:17"/>prohibit Practices by name and circumſtance,
then Popiſh Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and Monkery and ten thouſand other things, as
Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Owen</hi> well ſays, may be made Lawful by this Argument, there
being not an expreſs word in Scripture that prohibits thoſe things by their
very name, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not then in being. If it be meant what may be inferred
<hi>by direct and plain conſequence</hi> in the true <hi>Logical</hi> Notion
of it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sophiſtry or Quibble, I am ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied we can produce,
<hi>Precept, Preſident,</hi> and <hi>Example,</hi> that it is our Duty to
withdraw from diſorderly Walkers. And our Diſſenting Brethren grant, that
the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm, by <hi>Rantiſm</hi> or Sprinkling in
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy is diſorderly, as being a Practice without Example or Conſequent
Warrant from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and Adminiſtred to a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject not capable, or
qualified to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61819:17"/>it, nor in an orderly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. And
therefore it is ſo much the more wonderful, that they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove any, ſhould
blame us for obeying the Solemn Command we read, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6,
viz. <hi>Now we command you, brethren, in the name of our Lord Jeſus
Chriſt, that ye withdraw your ſelves from every brother that walketh
diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not after the Tradition which ye received of us.</hi> Which
laſt Phraſe<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> (the word [<hi>Paradoſis</hi>] ſignifying not
only Doctrine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.2,3. But alſo a Command,
Ordinance or Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, as before, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.15.) plainly
makes out that they were not only to withdraw from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of
<hi>diſorderly</hi> Converſation, or defective in <hi>Morals,</hi> but
alſo from ſuch as were corrupt in Doctrine, or diſorderly in their
Goſpel-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, that being as great a violation of Goſpel Order,
and as pernicious of Chriſtians as Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality,<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61819:18"/>which
muſt be granted, or elſe there is no Authority given to the Church to deal
with Members of corrupt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this <hi>Command</hi> being <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,</hi> includes all
diſorders of any kind, in <hi>Manners, Doctrine,</hi> or <hi>Practice,</hi>
and is a ſufficient War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant (were there no more) for our Obedience, to
exclude ſuch as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly practice the Ordinance of Baptiſm, from our
immediate Communion at the Lords Table, though not from our Love and Affection,
for we hope they walk according to their Light, and the Error being not ſo
fundamental as to endanger their Eternal ſtate, we eſteem them Chriſtian
Brethren and Saints, for whoſe further il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination we dayly put up our
Prayers.</p>
            <p>But in regard we are convinced (1.) That it is the Duty of all
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers to be Baptized in Water up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61819:18"/>Confeſſion of
their Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (2.) That none but ſuch ought to be Baptized.
(3.) That ſuch as Practiſe otherwiſe deviate from the Rule of the
Goſpel, and the Precedents Recorded there. (4.) That ſuch a Deviation is in
it ſelf diſorderly, and in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence dangerous, as bringing many
unregenerate Members into the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We conceive our ſelves
bound by the indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable Rule of our Duty, to bear our Teſtimony
againſt ſuch a Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and in the moſt Healing manner we can, to
diſcharge our ſelves from being countenancers, or abettors of it, which we
can do no other way (unleſs they will be reclaimed) then by withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from
thoſe diſorders; after the Example of the <hi>Primitive Saints,</hi> of the
<hi>Ancient Waldenſoe,</hi> our <hi>Modern Reformers,</hi> &amp;c. (5.) We
are ſatisfied that we are guilty of no <hi>Schiſm</hi> in that particular,
for<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61819:19"/>we ſeparate not from any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian as ſuch, but
hold Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion as far as we agree, and where we cannot agree, we dare not but
obey the Command before reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, though we expoſe our ſelves to worldly
inconveniencies by it; <hi>The leaſt particle of Divine Truth being more
valuable than any thing the world can preſent:</hi> for which our, Brethren
ſhould not blame us, but rather ſeriouſly examine our Reaſons and
Arguments, and then judge.</p>
            <p>The farther proſecution of this matter is referred to its proper
Head: And therefore we ſhall propoſe to conſideration the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
Inquiry, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſtion. <hi>Whether Perons <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized may Regularly be
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Communion of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:61819:19"/> To obviate a Cavil, which may be made, the
Reader may underſtand that under the term <hi>[<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbaptized]</hi> we
comprehend all perſons that either were never Baptized at all, or ſuch as
have been (as they call it) <hi>Chriſtned</hi> or Baptized (more properly
Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) in their Infancy. Now our Diſſenting Brethren with whom we have
to do, look upon this way to be abſolutely invalid, and ſo no Baptiſm
(elſe they would not be Baptized themſelves) and conſequently eſteem
all ſuch as Unbaptized: ſo that we need not prove what is granted, and
ſhall therefore proceed to examine the Queſtion in the following
Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:61819:20"/>
            <head>CHAP. II. Reaſons why <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbaptized Members may not be admitted
to the Lords Supper.</head>
            <p>THat perſons Unbaptized may regularly be admitted to the Communion
of the Lords Supper, is denied from theſe Reaſons:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe this Opinion tends to deſtroy the Nature, Ends,
and Uſes of theſe Goſpel Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The nature of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is
Spiritual, when rightly Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred: Was it not ſubmitted unto by the
Primitive Chriſtians? Was it not the firſt Act done by them, after their
Converſion? <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41,42. Whereby they became viſible
Profeſſors of the Goſpel of Truth, which figured their Death, Burial, and
Reſurrection with Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. 
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61819:20"/>Is it not an Inſtitution ſtampt with as Divine a
Character, and as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred a Sanction as any in Scripture? All Nations taught,
being to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, and being of the ſame duration with Preaching,
ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to by Chriſt himſelf, before he entred upon his Publick
Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry (which is the moſt Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Example</hi> in the World)
wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed unto by the Renowned Worthies of all Ages.</p>
            <p>Now that this Ordinance, being of that quality, enforced by ſo
great Authority, ſubmitted to by ſuch Examples, and ſerving for ſuch
gracious ends, (as to be the Symbol of Regeneration, in which a Believer is
made a Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of thoſe Divine Conveyances, thoſe communications of
Grace, and increaſings of Faith, promiſed by the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> to
his ſincere followers,) ſhould be put in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being quite aboliſht,
and the practiſe loſt by an unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61819:21"/>and
miſtaken apprehenſion, and that by ſuch perſons as own Baptiſm to be
as here repreſented, is a matter ſomething ſtrange, and 'tis to be
feared, will prove in the conſequence of ill Effect, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to this but
the ſucceeding Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, if they that Eſpouſe it ſhould go about to
propagate this new Principle: to prevent which, (if it may pleaſe the Divine
Will to bleſs theſe lines) was the only end of this Eſſay, and that
purely out of the Zeal I have to preſerve (as much as in me lies) the
Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in their purity, as they were delivered to us by Chriſt; for we
all know what a vaſt trouble and hazard the Reformers (and indeed many that
are alive at preſent) had to Reſcue this as well other Truths and
Ordinances, from the Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Additions of Sanguinary Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting
Romaniſts, under whoſe Captivity it groaned for ſome Ages.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:61819:21"/>To enforce what is ſaid, I ſhall endeavour
to ſhew here ſome of the ill conſequences of this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and the
ſmall reaſon our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren have to propagate it, though I ſtill reſerve
much to the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Objections, where their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons will be more largly
reply'd to.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This Opinion has a direct tendency to invalidate, or
indeed, quite throw out of doors, and diſcontinue the uſe of a Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
Ordinance, or Principle of the Goſpel of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. For if
Unbaptized Perſons may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to all Church Priviledges, does not
ſuch a practice plainly ſuppoſe that it is unneceſſary? 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Supra ſic per plura quod ſieri poteſt
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ciora.</hi>
               </note>for to what
purpoſe is it to be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed (may one Reaſon with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) if he may
enjoy all Church Priviledges without it? The <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> (if once
ſuch a belief pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails,) would be eaſily tempted to lay aſide that
reproached Practice, <pb n="14" facs="tcp:61819:22"/>(which Envious Men have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly
derided and aſperſed,) of being <hi>dipt,</hi> that is Baptized, and
challenge their Church Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion by vertue of their Faith only; and ſuch as
Baptized Infants would be ſatisfied to diſcontinue the practice, when one
they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that their Children may be Regular Church-Members
without it; for if it be ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, diſcreet and thrifty People would
willingly be rid of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Chriſtning-Feaſts, (as they call them)
and all the appurtenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereto belonging: ſo that in a ſhort time we
ſhould have neither old nor young baptized, and by conſequence be in a
likely condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to loſe one of the Sacraments, which would eaſily make
way for the loſs of the other, both having an equal Sanction in Scripture;
and the Arguments that diſanul the one, will deſtroy the other, and
conſequently all Ordinances,<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61819:22"/>and Modes of Worſhip, and
laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Religion it ſelf. For if a thing expreſly commanded, and
practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Chriſt, be lookt upon as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary, every man will
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that 'tis all one, whether he takes or leaves it, and will, if he
can chooſe, rather leave it, ſince the taking it up, is ſomthing
trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome and of no uſe, (as is ſuppoſed) which begets an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,
That Chriſts Laws may be diſpens'd withal by men, and ſo leſſens that
Reverence and Eſteem which perſons ought to have for Chriſt: and when
ſuch do once make a Breach in thoſe Boundaries &amp; Limits, which they are
enjoyned not to paſs, they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſtop in that extravagant Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer till
they run beyond all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion into Atheiſm, or pretended Enthuſiaſm. So
that (at beſt) this Opinion tends to encourage perſons in the neglect or
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Religious Duty, or to <pb n="16" facs="tcp:61819:23"/>the loſs thereof quite
and clean; which is, no leſs, than to be, not only an Acceſſary, but (in
a great meaſure) the Cauſe of that ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Opinion gives up a Cauſe and Truth that has been by
judicious Pens well Defended both from Scripture and Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and which
theſe Brethren themſelves are convinced to be a Goſpel Truth: for if it
be once admitted that it is not neceſſary to Church-Communion, every Man of
ſence will infer, That our contentions for it were frivolous, our Separation
Schiſmatical, and our Suffering the Penalties of Humane Laws, fooliſh: and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, we ſhall be expoſed to the Reproaches of ſuch as are
(without this advantage) ready enough to Revile and Perſecute us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Opinion perverts or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſtroys Order: &amp;
flatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts the Practice of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61819:23"/>Chriſtians; It is ſaid, <hi>Act</hi> 2.41. <hi>Then they that
gladly received his Word were Baptized.</hi> Here is the right Goſpel Order,
Firſt, <hi>they that gladly received the Word;</hi> that is, they that
believed, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>were</hi> immediately <hi>Baptiſed,</hi> (that
it was immediately, appears by the Adverb <hi>then</hi>) which was the ſecond
Work, <hi>and the ſame day</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> after they believed and were
Baptized) <hi>there were added unto them,</hi> (that is, received into
Church-Fellowſhip, by Faith and Baptiſm) <hi>about Three thouſand
Souls.</hi> ver. 42. <hi>And they continued ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly in the Apoſtles
Doctrine and Fellowſhip</hi> (that is in the ſame Faith and Communion,)
<hi>and in break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Bread and Prayers</hi> (that is in the enjoyment and
Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Church Ordinances:) Is not here a famous Inſtance or
Preſident of their Practice, which anſwers thoſe frequent and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
Clamours of ſuch, who call<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61819:24"/>for <hi>Scripture to juſtifie
the Excluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our holy Brethren that have not been ſo
Baptized.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2. Theſſ. 3.6.</note> Whereas in the
fore-going Pages, there is a Scripture cited, That juſtifies our withdrawing
from diſorderly walkers; and ſuch as make this Out-cry own the practices of
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Baptiſm in that particular to be ſuch, and therefore our
Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for that Reaſon (purſuant to that Expreſs Command) lawful;
which they muſt grant, or deny <hi>Infant Baptiſm</hi> to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly;
or elſe muſt ſay, that there be ſome diſorderly walkers, that we may
and ought to have Communion with, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſolemn Prohibition
of it, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is ſaid, That Baptiſm was never Ordained of God
to be a Wall of Diviſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the holy, and the holy; the holy that are,
and the holy that are not <hi>ſo</hi> Baptized with<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61819:24"/>Water,
as we, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is Anſwered,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Phraſe [Wall of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion] is ambiguous; If it be
meant of a total Excluſion of other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians from our Love, Charity, and
Chriſtian-Communion, as far as we agree; we do not look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Baptiſm to be
ſuch a Wall of Diviſion, neither do we ſo practice it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If it be meant, of an Exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from immediate
Church-fellowſhip, although we meet not with this Phraſe, [<hi>viz.</hi>
Wall of Diviſion] in thoſe very words, yet we find what is equivalent in 2
<hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6. and ſeveral other Texts: and it is remarkable, that
the Word Tranſlated 
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>ex a priv. &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Ordinatus.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<hi>inordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus vel ex ordine,</hi> out of Order.</note>
               <hi>diſorderly,</hi> is a <hi>metaphor</hi> borrowed from the Cuſtom of
War, wherein every Souldier hath his Station aſſigned him, from which, when
he <hi>ſwerves,</hi> he becomes diſorderly, which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>
Elegantly uſes, to denote, That every Chriſtian is a Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61819:25"/>that's Liſted under the Banner of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and
muſt keep his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Station appointed him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt inclining to
the right or left hand, backward or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, without the Word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.
<hi>Beza</hi> upon the place tells us, that <hi>Livius</hi> was wont to uſe
this word of Soldiers, that kept not their Station: And <hi>Stephanus</hi>
calls thoſe Souldiers by this Name, who are diſorderly. From this
<hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis</hi> of the word, we may gather, That if Military Commanders
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a punctual and regular Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience from their Soldiers; and ſeverely
puniſh ſuch as break their Array, or quit their Stations; The <hi>Lord</hi>
(who is a Jealous God with reſpect to his Worſhip, and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
Inſtitutions) will call any, that preſume to break the Order he has
preſcribed, to a ſevere account, as hath been, and ſhall be further
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Aſſertion reaches any<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61819:25"/>other
Goſpel-Ordinance, as well as <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> For if it ſhould be
ſaid, That the <hi>Supper</hi> was never Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God to be a Wall of
Diviſion between the Holy and the Holy, that do not ſo receive it as we, it
will as rationally fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low with reſpect to this, as well as
<hi>Baptiſm,</hi> that we ſhould not exclude a perſon that doubts it, or
poſitively aſſerts it to be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, from our Communion, which may be
likewiſe ſaid of any Church-Ordinance whatſoever; and conſequently, the
Rule of Communion muſt not be what we find written, but the Sanctity of the
Party (whether pretended or real) that propoſes himſelf as a Member. For I
would ask thoſe that pretend tenderneſs, and for that cauſe admit
Perſons to the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> that are Unbaptized, that if any
perſon ſhould deſire to joyn to a Church, and yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, he wants
Light to practice<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61819:26"/>the Ordinance of the <hi>Supper,</hi> but
in other things would be of their Communion, whether they would admit him upon
thoſe terms, he wanting Light in that Ordinance of <hi>Chriſt</hi> wherein
the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church doth chiefly conſiſt? If they would admit him,
they open ſo wide a gap, that any Ordinance upon the like pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence may be
diſpenced with, and two or three, yea all, as well as one, may be
Caſhier'd, and <hi>Church-Order</hi> may be quite turned to an
<hi>Anarchy.</hi> If they would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a perſon upon the ſaid terms,
then 'tis neceſſary to produce ſome Divine Law that makes the
<hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> more Eſſential than <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> or elſe the
practice can never be juſtified. But that no ſuch Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity can be
ſhewn, is undenyable; for that <hi>Divine Law</hi> that Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the
<hi>Supper,</hi> did alſo Eſtabliſh <hi>Baptiſm.</hi> If it be ſaid,
<hi>Matt.</hi> 26.26. Luk. 22.19. 1 Cor. 11.<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61819:26"/>24. <hi>Take
eate, this is my Body. This do in Remembrance of me,</hi> &amp;c. It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
ſaid, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Go teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Baptizing them in the
Name of the Father, and of the Son and holy Ghoſt.</hi> Act. 2.38. <hi>Repent
&amp; be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed every one of you for the Remiſſion of Sins,</hi> &amp;c.
Act. 22.16. <hi>Ariſe and be Baptized, &amp; waſh away thy Sins,</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>Do the <hi>former</hi> Scriptures Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute the <hi>Supper,</hi>
and Command its conſtant Obſervation? The <hi>lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> do as well
Inſtitute <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and Command its conſtant Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, the
very ſame Sanction, the ſame Spirit, with equal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority Eſtabliſhes
both, giving <hi>Baptiſm</hi> precedency in <hi>order of time,</hi> as being
the Sacrament of the Spiritual <hi>Birth,</hi> and the other of Spiritual
<hi>Nouriſhment</hi> and <hi>Growth;</hi> and ſurely there is as much need
of being <hi>New Born,</hi> as being <hi>Spiritually fed,</hi> that being of
abſolute neceſſity with reſpect to priority, in order to this.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:61819:27"/>Did <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf Celebrate this
<hi>Supper,</hi> as before? Why the ſame Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> before he
entred upon his Publick Miniſtry, was Baptized, <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.16,17.
<hi>And Jeſus when he was Baptized, went up ſtraight-way out of the Water:
and lo the Heavens were opened to him, and he ſaw the Spirit of God
deſcending like a Dove, and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him; ſaying, This is my beloved
Son, in whom I am well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> Here the whole <hi>Trinity</hi>
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, the <hi>Father</hi> by a Voice, the <hi>Son</hi> in his Body, and the
<hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> like a Dove: All Three make the Triumph, and Ratifie the
Affair; never was any Ordinance graced with ſuch a Preſence, nor made
Authentick by a more Illuſtrious Example.</p>
            <p>Does the <hi>Supper ſhew forth the Lords Death till he come?</hi>
1 Cor- 11.26. So <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is a lively ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol of the <hi>Death,
Burial, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Col.</hi>
2.12.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:61819:27"/>Does <hi>Examination</hi> go before the
<hi>Supper?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. So <hi>Faith</hi> and
<hi>Repentance,</hi> the two great Goſpel Graces, with Confeſſion of
ſins, are neceſſary Antecedents to Baptiſm, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38.
<hi>Act.</hi> 8.37. and all theſe are altogether as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary before the
Supper.</p>
            <p>Is it ſaid <hi>John</hi> 6.54. <hi>Whoſo eateth my fleſh and
drinketh my blood, hath eternal life?</hi> &amp;c. So it is ſaid
<hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth and is baptized ſhall be
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> &amp;c. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. <hi>The like figure whereunto,
even Baptiſm doth alſo now ſave us,</hi> (not the putting <hi>away the
filth of the fleſh, but the 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Stipulatio.</hi>
                  </note>ſtipulation</hi> (or anſwer) <hi>of
a good Conſcience toward God, by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
As the <hi>Supper</hi> is a Spiritual parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of the <hi>Body and
Blood</hi> of Chriſt by Faith, and ſo (not meerly by the work done) is a
means of Salvation; ſo <hi>Baptiſm Signs</hi> and <hi>Seals</hi> our
Salvation to<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61819:28"/>us, which lies in <hi>Juſtification</hi> and
diſcharge of ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this brief <hi>Parallel</hi> we may ſee that <hi>Baptiſm</hi>
is not only or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and ratified by the great Law-giver, as well as the
Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but that it is dignified with as Spiritual <hi>Encomiums</hi> as any
Goſpel Ordinance can be; and if the advantage inclines to either of them, it
is evident that the New Teſtament more frequently men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the Command and
Practice of Baptiſm than of the Supper: for beſides the Great
Commiſſion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15,16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
you have frequent <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Examples</hi> of it. <hi>Act.</hi>
2.38. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.38. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.18. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.48.
<hi>Act.</hi> 16.15,33. <hi>Act.</hi> 18.8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we
find any one Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the New Teſtament ſo made uſe of by the
Apoſtle to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite Chriſtians to dye to ſin and live to God, as this
Ordinance of Baptiſm, being that which <pb n="27" facs="tcp:61819:28"/>is ſignified
thereby is called a <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial with Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 6.4. <hi>A put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on
of Chriſt.</hi> Gal. 3.27. <hi>The ſignification of the waſhing away of
our ſins by the blood of Chriſt,</hi> Act. 22.16. That having an intereſt
in Chriſt, and being buryed with him, <hi>We may walk in newneſs of
life,</hi> &amp;c. Whereas beſides the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Lords
<hi>Supper</hi> by Jeſus Chriſt, inſtanced by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
Evangeliſts, that Ordinance is but four times mentioned, <hi>viz. Act.</hi>
2.42. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. and 11.23. By all which it
appears that the Ordinance of Baptiſm, as it has the <hi>Precedency</hi> in
point of Order, ſo it is more frequently mentioned, and more earneſtly
inculcated, than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; therefore the <hi>Obligation</hi> to
preſerve it, as <hi>Delivered by Chriſt and his Apoſtles,</hi> is
indiſpenſable.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In regard it is granted by ſuch as hold the opinion here
argued againſt, that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, 
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61819:29"/>&amp;c.</hi> are <hi>poſitive Inſtitutions</hi> It will
unavoidably follow, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the
Force and Authority they have upon the Conſcience in point of Practice, is to
be derived from the plain expreſs <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Word</hi> of God,
which made them Ordinances; from whence only we are to ſeek both a Warrant
for, and the Method and manner of Practiſing them. The Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction given to
<hi>Moſes</hi> was, <hi>See that thou make ALL things according to the
PATTERN ſhewed thee in the Mount, Heb.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.9. to 40.
And no leſs exact are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to be in the Adminiſtration of Goſpel
Ordinances; ſince to deviate from the expreſs Rule, is branded with the
odious Title of <hi>Will-Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>humane Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All Sound and Orthodox Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with one mind agree (and meer
Reaſon teaches it) that where a <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>expreſs Law</hi> is 
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61819:29"/>preſcribed to men, that very <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription,</hi> is
an expreſs prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the contrary: 
<note place="margin">Act. 2.38. to 42.</note>Here we have the Order of
Goſpel Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not only Commanded, but Practiſed. Firſt they
Preached; and ſuch as were Converted, were Baptized; ſuch as were Baptized,
walkt in Church-Fellowſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Breaking of Bread and Prayers;
which being ſo expreſs, what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity is there to be wiſe above
what is written, and to clamour for <hi>Precept</hi> or <hi>Example,</hi> to
prove that Baptiſm is a bar to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſince we read every where,
(where Goſpel order is ſet down,) that all ſuch as were received, were
firſt Baptized; and not one inſtance in the whole Bible, that any were
received without it. Nor is it rational to think that any were admitted to
Church-Fellowſhip any other way, unleſs we will ſay that theſe
poſitive <hi>Precepts</hi> were calculated for ſome<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61819:30"/>only, and not for all Chriſtians, which is not only abſurd, but
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the very Letter of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Teach
all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Baptizing them,</hi> that is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry individual that gladly
receives the Word in every <hi>Nation: Take Eat,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Drink ye all
of it,</hi> Matth. 26.26. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That is, every indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Member of
the Church. Which Interpretation muſt needs ſtand, until the Maintainers of
this new Opinion can aſſign to what ſort of Chriſtians theſe Divine
<hi>Precepts</hi> are obligatory, and to what ſort they are not; a thing
impoſſible to be made out. Which I ſhall ſhut up in the words of Mr.
<hi>Coxe,</hi> in his late <hi>Diſcourſe of the Covenants,</hi> page 131.
<hi>In matters of</hi> Poſitive Right (ſaith he) <hi>we can have no warrant
for our practice, but from a</hi> Poſitive Precept: <hi>for things of this
kind fall not within the compaſs of</hi> Common Light, <hi>or ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
Principles of Natural Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61819:30"/>but have their Original
from</hi> a particular, diſtinct, and indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Will of the Law-giver.
<hi>And therefore Inferences built upon Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Notions may ſoon lead us
into miſtakes about them; if upon ſuch inferences we</hi> Form <hi>a</hi>
Rule <hi>to our ſelves of</hi> larger extent <hi>than</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
words of the Inſtitution <hi>do warrant.</hi> Which as it is a ſound and
excellent Truth, quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws this practice of admitting Unbaptized
perſons to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Lords Supper, there being no poſitive
<hi>Precept</hi> to warrant it:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quere how
conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and therefore is que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried how this their
Opinion can be conſiſtent, or reconciled with theſe expreſſions?</p>
            <p>To conclude: The ends and uſes of Baptiſm being (1.) To
repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Eye and Underſtanding by a viſible ſign or figure
what hath been Preacht to the Ear and Heart. (2.) To witneſs Repentance,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 3.6,11. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. <hi>Mark</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:61819:31"/>1.4. (3.) To evidence Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, called in alluſion to it the
waſhing of Regeneration, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. A being born of the Water and the
Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 3.5. (4.) A Symbol of our dying unto ſin, and living
again to Chriſtian newneſs of life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12.
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is therefore an Ordinance of very great ſignificancy, and
ſuch as go about to lay it aſide, (as this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in its tendency and
Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence muſt needs do) deſerve no thanks from the Churches of
Chriſt, who have experienced much of the Lords preſence in its Regular and
Orderly Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:61819:31"/>
            <head>CHAP. III. Shews that this Practice of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Unbaptized
Perſons to the Lords Supper, is againſt Scripture.</head>
            <p>TO Demonſtrate this Truth we ſhall add ſome further
enforcements from that Text be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
11.2. <hi>Now I praiſe you Brethren, that ye remember me in all things, and
keep the 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Syriack. Manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutum,</hi>
an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet. Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta mea tenetis,</hi> and keep my Precepts.
<hi>Montanus.</hi>
                  </note>Ordinances as I delivered them unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle having in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Chapter, verſe 14.
exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to fly from Idolatry, ſhewing the great danger of mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in
the Worſhip of God, in verſe 22. brings them to conſider the danger;
<hi>Do we provoke the<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61819:32"/>Lord to 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ad i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, vel ad aemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landi ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voco,</hi> To
provoke to wrath or jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</note>jealouſie? Are we ſtronger than
he?</hi> And ver. 23. to prevent all miſtakes ſheweth that in things of an
indifferent Nature, there might be a lawful uſe of them provided therein all
oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of offence were avoided. And elſewhere (<hi>viz. Rom.</hi> 14.)
he Treats largely of the duty of Saints to bear one with another, and not to
with draw their Love and Affections from each other, where the matter of
difference lay only in ſuch things, as in themſelves had no relation to the
Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he exhorts them to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers
of him as he was of Chriſt, by which he informs them that no mans Practiſe
or Example ought to be any further followed than they follow Chriſt.</p>
            <p>In the Text he commends them for their care in keeping the
Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt pure, both with<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61819:32"/>reſpect to matter
and form, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the Phraſe <hi>[as they were delivered unto
you]</hi> from whence we may obſerve,</p>
            <p>That it is Practiſe praiſe worthy for the Churches of Jeſus
Chriſt to preſerve and keep the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt, as they have been
delivered by Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to them. becauſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We hereby advance the Wiſdom of Jeſus Chriſt, who
hath in his Houſe ordered all things ſo, to the effecting of thoſe ends
for which he hath appointed them, that there is no neceſſity of mans
Additions, either with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the matter of them, or the Order and
Method in which they are diſpoſed. Now the Church of Chriſt is his
Houſe, and his Wiſdom ſhines greatly, not only in the Food he hath
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for them, but in the way by which they receive it from him, there
being nothing that<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61819:33"/>intrencheth more upon the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of
God, than that (when he hath preſcribed a method in his Word) men ſhould
preſume to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or change the ſame; it being a much greater ſin than
the bare O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of any Duty, for by our O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions we ſhew only
our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſhortneſs of what we ſhould know and do; but by
Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, we caſt a blemiſh upon the Wiſdom of Chriſt, as if we were
wiſer to order things than he.</p>
            <p>That which occaſioned ſo great an aſtoniſhment in the Queen
of <hi>Sheba,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.4,5,8. Was the obſervation of the
Order of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> Houſe, which made her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire his Wiſdom. And
ſurely the Wiſdom of Chriſt is very eminently ſeen in the Order wherein
the Ordinances of his Houſe ought to be Practiſed. The Apoſtle,
<hi>Col.</hi> 2.5. Rejoyced to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold not only the ſtedfaſtneſs of their
Faith, but their Order alſo<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61819:33"/>in the Goſpel of Jeſus
Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the Ordinances of Chriſt are given by him to
his people as a Truſt, and therefore great care and fidelity muſt be uſed
to keep them as they were delivered by him: For as in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Affairs, the
exact conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and upright management of a Truſt, is a certain note
of the Integrity and Honeſty of the Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtee, ſo the violation of it is a
high breach and violation of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and Faithfulneſs. Hence the Apoſtle
ſo earneſtly exhorts <hi>Timothy</hi> to <hi>keep that which was committed
to his truſt,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> any thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſited, or credited to ones faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and
truſt.</note> 2 Tim. 6.20. Yea, the glorious Goſpel it ſelf, (of which
this Holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is a part) is ſaid to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Apoſtles
Truſt, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 1.11. And ſo it is indeed committed to the Care and
Truſt of all True Churches of Chriſt, who are to be accountable for it, to
the Great Lord and Author<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61819:34"/>of it the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe it preſerves the Beauty of the Houſe of God:
For whatſoever is preſcribed by the Lord Jeſus, with reſpect to his
Worſhip, is full of Beauty, Harmony, and Order, every thing anſwering its
reſpective end, and what is ſignified there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by: and as Grace ſhines in
its luſtre in the orderly exerciſe thereof; ſo do the Ordinances of
Chriſt: For as Regeneration is the firſt work of God upon the Soul, in
order to the exerciſe of the Graces of Chriſt given, ſo hath he appointed
Baptiſm, as that which is the firſt Ordinance to be Practiſed, which doth
more particularly, than any other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance in the ſignification of it,
hold out, and viſibly repreſent our New Birth, and therefore is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the
Baptiſm of Repentance, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.4. <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.3.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:61819:34"/>Sutable hereunto does that Learned and Eminent
Divine Mr. <hi>Daniel Rogers</hi> expreſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. 
<q rend="inline">
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Treat. of the two Sacram.
<hi>p.</hi> 71. Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, 1633.</note>'Baptiſm then is the Firſt Sacrament
of the Goſpel, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Water, which is Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally Chriſt; or
wherein by Water duly applyed, not only the preſented party is made a Member
of the viſible Church; but alſo Sealed up to an inviſible Union with
Chriſt, and thereby intereſſed in all thoſe benefits of his, which
concern the being of Regeneration.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'By calling it the firſt Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I point at
the Precedency and Order of Baptiſm. The which all thoſe Names of
Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm both in Scripture, and elſe where do approve Its the Seed of the
Church, as the other is of Food. It iſſued firſt out of the ſide of our
Lord Jeſus upon the Croſs. Its the Creating Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God to produce
and form<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61819:35"/>the Lord Jeſus to a New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to
Regeneration in the Soul. 
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.5.</note> Its called our Union with
Chriſt, our Marriage Ring, our Military Preſs-mony, our Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation,
Cognizance and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Chriſt, our Implanting or Ingrafting into him,
and his Body, our Ship, our Ark, our Red Sea, our putting on of Chriſt. For
as all thoſe go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Nouriſhment, Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, Cohabitation,
ſervice, Fruit, Manna, or Food from Heaven, ſo this Sacrament muſt go
before the other. Breeding, Begetting and bringing out of the Womb, doth not
more Naturally go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the feeding of the Infant by the mothers Breaſts,
then this Womb of the Youth of the Church goes before the Milk thereof; the
Church being no Dry Nurſe, but a Mother of her own, the Sons and Daughters of
her own Womb—Let all who<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61819:35"/>deſire to taſte of the
Sealing power of the ſecond Sacrament to Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh them as Saints: Firſt
prove the Sealing power of the former Sacrament to beget and make you Saints.
<hi>And a little after</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag.
72</note>—Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware—leſt the Lord be froward with them that fight
againſt the God of Order: leſt inſtead of finding Nouriſhment before
Breeding, as they Rob God of his Order, ſo they meet with Wrath and Judgment,
before Mercy and Salvation; yea leſt God accurſe their ſingle emptyneſs
of Chriſt, with ſuch a double barrenneſs, as will admit no Conception or
Birth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>'<hi>And very pathetically pag.</hi> 73. after he hath ſhewed that
Chriſt hath joyned Water with a kind of equal neceſſity with himſelf,
<hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. <hi>John</hi> 3.5. <hi>ſubjoyns</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">'Shall not he who deſpiſeth Water (appointed to
ſuch an unſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Holy end) deſpiſe the Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61819:36"/>of Water? 
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.7.</note> ſhall we take his name in
vain, by ſlighting that by which he makes himſelf and the power of his Word
and Spirit manifeſt to beget the Soul to him, and be holden guiltleſs? 
<note place="margin">Matth. 19.6.</note> When Chriſt hath put both
in one, ſhall we dare to ſay the one is ſtrong, the other is baſe?
ſhall we ſlight it, ſlack our haſte to it, our Holy preparing of our
ſelves to it, our abiding at it, our offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up Prayers for bleſſing
it, our making it the joynt Object of our Humiliation, Faith, Reverence, and
Thanks? Far be it from us, ſo to abhor that Popiſh <hi>Hyperbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical</hi>
eſteem of it, and the merit of the work wrought of it; that we run into
another Riot to diſeſteem it? Doubtleſs he that cares not for Chriſt in
the Word, Chriſt in the Promiſe, Chriſt in the Miniſter, Chriſt in
the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Chriſt in the Bread and Wine, Chriſt Sacramental; cares 
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61819:36"/>as little for Chriſt God, Chriſt Fleſh, Chriſt
<hi>Emanuel.</hi> By theſe he comes near. And 
<note place="margin">Matth. 10.40.</note>
                  <hi>He that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth
you, deſpiſeth me, and him that ſent me.</hi> Beware we of ſuch
contempt, even in the ſecreteſt of our thoughts and Affections: and let
Chriſt in the Water be Honoured as Chriſt, for that ſweet Union and Fruit
which he brings to poor Souls thereby. If <hi>Jordan</hi> be precious when God
will uſe it, for the Angels Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by it, much more this.<note place="margin">2 Kings 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. John
5.2.</note>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'<hi>Pag.</hi> 81. The Lords Scope in Baptiſm is
an inward Grace, but this general Priviledge is to all equal, <hi>viz.</hi> A
badge of an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Member: diſtinction from the common Rout of the World,
out of the Pale of the Church. The Lord appointed Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a Seal of
the Righteouſneſs of Faith chiefly: yet as an over-plus he allowed it to be
the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencer of all other Nations from<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61819:37"/>the
<hi>Jews.</hi> It was a Fence and Wall of Separation from them in all their
Converſe. So is Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm now a mark or badge of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Communion:
whereby the Lord ſettles a Right upon the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to his Ordinances, that
he may comfortably uſe them as his own Priviledge, and wait for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
Prerogative of Saints by them. And yet this (as much as men boaſt of it) is
but a ſhell in reſpect of the other.</q> So far he.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Baptiſm</hi> holds out the Souls Intereſt in the
Death, Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and Reſurrection of Chriſt in a more ſpecial manner then
any other Ordinance, it is called the Stipulation or Anſwer of a good
Conſcience, by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the Dead;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.21.</note> that is, when a Conſcience ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed and
pacified with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of Sin, can cry <hi>Abba Father</hi> with a holy
ſecurity, and ſpeak to God himſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now this
Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61819:37"/>of a good Conſcience is the Effect of
<hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and which <hi>Baptiſm</hi> Seals: For what it finds
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Seals, although it doth alſo
Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit more of the ſame kind. A <hi>Learned Expoſitor</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Tho. Godwin.</hi>
               </note> gives his Senſe of this place
thus.</p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'The Anſwer of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is here
Attributed to Chriſts Reſurrection, as the thing ſignified and
repreſented in <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> and as the cauſe of that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of a
good Conſcience, even <hi>Baptiſm</hi> (ſaith he) doth now ſave
<hi>[us]</hi> as being the Ordinance that Seals up Salvation, not the putting
away the filth of the Fleſh, or the waſhing of the outward man; but the
Anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God by the Reſurrection of Chriſt
from the Dead. (To open this, <hi>ſaith he</hi>) Our Conſcienccs are that
Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple within us, which are the Seat of the guilt of all the Sins of the
whole Man, unto whoſe Court<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61819:38"/>they all come to accuſe us,
as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods Deputy, which Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is called Good or Evil, as the State
of the Man is. Now in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> forgiveneſs of Sins and
Juſtification being Sealed up to a Believers Faith and Conſcience under
that lively Repreſentation of his Communion with Chriſt in his
Reſurrection; hence this is made the fruit of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> that the
good Conſcience of a Believer Sealed up in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> hath
where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal from thence to Anſwer all Accuſations of Sin that can or do at
any time come in upon him, and is, as it is here added (by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the
Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt,) namely in this Reſpect, that his
Communion with Chriſt in his Reſurrection hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in his
<hi>Baptiſm</hi> as the Ground of his Faith, and of that Anſwer unto all
Accuſations.</q>
            </p>
            <p>By all which we may (by the way) ſee of what neceſſity Faith 
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61819:38"/>is required of the Perſons that are <hi>Baptized,</hi> if
they will receive any benefit thereby. Alſo, how <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> being
the firſt Ordinance to be Adminiſtred, anſwers to the firſt Grace
Received; From whence it appeareth, That as the Grace of Regeneration gives a
Right to the Enjoyment of Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Inſtitutions; ſo <hi>Baptiſm,</hi>
with reſpect to Priority and Order, is the firſt Inſtitution, without
which, none may regularly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of other Church-Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>And this further may be noted as conſiderable, that as there is
but one Beginning of Natural Life to man; and one beginning of Spiritual of
Life, which is by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, <hi>John</hi> 3.3. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ames Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulla</hi> The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol. <hi>pag.</hi> 183
The Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lord ought of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes to be Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to the ſame
Perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> So <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is to be but once
Adminiſtred; whereas, if <hi>Baptiſm</hi> had the ſame import and
ſignification with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Priviledges that are to be enjoy'd at
the Second Coming<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61819:39"/>of Chriſt as the Supper of the Lord
hath, there would be the ſame Reaſon for the frequent Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of
it, as is for the Supper of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is commendable to keep the Ordinances of Chriſt pure,
as they were delivered, becauſe it prevents the creeping in of the
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions of Men in the Worſhip of God. For (as it was before Noted) Man is
naturally apt to be medling that way, and mixing ſomething of his own with
thoſe Sacred Inſtitutions which God has with greateſt ſeverity
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited, having not ſpared any, no not his own People, though what they
have done therein ſeems not to be out of any wicked intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but rather
out of an Ignorant Zeal: Of which there are many Inſtances in Scripture as
before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited; particularly, the Memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Caſes of <hi>Nadab</hi> and
<hi>Abihu,</hi> Lev. 10.2,3. Uzzah 2 Sam. 6.6,7. &amp;<hi>c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:61819:39"/>Suitable hereto Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> very
excellently expreſſes himſelf in his Book intituled
<hi>Goſpel-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or the Right Manner of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying the Name of
God,</hi> pag 8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">—'All things in Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip muſt have a
Warrant out of Gods Word, muſt be Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; it's not enough that 'tis not
Forbidden, and what hurt is there in it? But it muſt be
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.—When we come to <hi>Matters of Religion</hi> and the
<hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God,</hi> we muſt either have a <hi>Command,</hi> or
ſomewhat out of <hi>Gods Word,</hi> by ſome Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence drawn from
ſome <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> wherein God manifeſts his Will; either a <hi>Direct
Command,</hi> or by comparing one thing with another, or drawing
Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>plainly</hi> from the words, we muſt have a
<hi>Warrant</hi> for the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—When
any Creature is raiſed in a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <pb n="50" facs="tcp:61819:40"/>way above what it
hath in it by Nature, if I have not <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> to <hi>warrant</hi> me,
I am therein <hi>Superſtitious.</hi>—We muſt be all
<hi>Willing-Worſhippers,</hi> but not <hi>Will-Worſhippers, Matth.</hi>
15.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 10. 
<q rend="inline">'—You ſee how ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere God was to
<hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu,</hi> for but taking <hi>other Fire</hi> then
that which God appointed, to offer up Incenſe, though there there was no
direct Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>againſt</hi> it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 11. 
<q rend="inline">'In the matters of <hi>Worſhip</hi> God ſtands
up <hi>little</hi> things, ſuch things as ſeem to be very ſmall and
little to us, yet God ſtands much upon them in the matter of Worſhip. For
there is nothing wherein the Prerogative of God doth more appear, then in
Worſhip, as Princes ſtand much upon their Prerogatives.—There
are—things in the Worſhip of God<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61819:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>that are not
written in our <hi>hearts,</hi> that only depend upon the will of God Revealed
in his Word; which were no Duties except they were Revealed there. And theſe
are of ſuch a nature, as we can ſee no Reaſon for, but only this,
<hi>Becauſe God will have them.</hi>—Though men would think it a little
matter whether <hi>this</hi> Fire, or <hi>that</hi> Fire, and will not
<hi>this</hi> burn as well as <hi>that?</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t God ſtands upon it.—When
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> did but touch the Ark, when it was ready to fall, we would
think it no great matter; but one touch of the Ark coſt him his life. There
is not a <hi>min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim</hi> in the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> but
<hi>God</hi> ſtands mightily upon it.—For a man 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.32.</note> to gather a
few ſticks (on the Sabbath) what great great matter was it? But <hi>God</hi>
ſtands upon it. So when the men of <hi>Bethſhemeſh</hi> did but look into
the Ark, it coſt the Lives of<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61819:41"/>fifty thouſand and
ſeventy men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He further adds, page 12. <hi>That there is no Priviledges or
Dignities of Man, that can ſecure them from Gods ſtroke;</hi> Inſtancing
<hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi>'s Caſe, <hi>Moſes the man of God being
their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkle, and Aaron their Father, men newly conſecrated to the Prieſts
Office, renowned men that God put much glory upon; yet if they will venture but
to offend God in this little thing, his wrath breaks out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and kills
them preſently,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Eminent Servant of God Adds much to the ſame effect in the
ſaid Book which for Brevity is paſt over—And amongſt the Reſt,
offers ſeveral Reaſons by which he judgeth that <hi>Nadab</hi> and
<hi>Abihu,</hi> were good men, and gives a plain Demonſtration that they had
no wicked Deſign, as [1] They were Young men, newly come to their Office, and
might not underſtand<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61819:41"/>all things, as if they had had
lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Experience. [2] Its obſervable for ver. 1. 'Tis called <hi>ſtrange
fire, which he Commanded not,</hi> that if there be not a Command for our
Practice, nor ſuch a Preſident as the Scripture approves of, no Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<hi>pretence</hi> can excuſe the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor from the Judgment of
God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beza,</hi> In his Annotations upon the third verſ. <hi>I will
be ſanctified,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves that the meaning of it is,—<hi>I will
puniſh them that ſerve me o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then I have Commanded, not ſparing
the Cheif, that the People may fear and praiſe my Judgments.</hi> There is
alſo a notable Inſtance, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.13,15,19. Concerning the men of
<hi>Beſhemeſh,</hi> who being in the field reaping their Harveſt,
Rejoyced at its Return, ver. 13. And therefore offered Sacrifices to the Lord,
ver. 15. But becauſe they looked into the Ark, fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand,
threeſcore and ten men of<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61819:42"/>them (as was ſaid) were
ſlain. The like inſtance we have (as was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready urged) about
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.6. whom God ſmites dead for touching the
Ark, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is concluded by all Orthodox <hi>Writers,</hi> that the Riſe of
Antichriſt was by Degrees; firſt encroaching by one Invention, and then
from time to time ſuper-adding another; which is indeed no wonder, for if a
Church once ſwerves from the Rule in one thing, a Foundation is thereby laid
of doing ſo in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things. And for this Reaſon the Apoſtle with great
Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs charges, 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tim.</hi>
6.13,14.</note>
               <hi>Timothy,</hi> and in him all Saints, thus, <hi>I give thee
charge in the ſight of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That thou keep this Commandment
without ſpot, unrebukeable, until the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of our Lord Jeſus
Chriſt.</hi> The Apoſtle had in this Epiſtle been inſtructing
<hi>Timothy</hi> about Church-VVorſhip, and things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing to Prayer, Elderſhip, deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61819:42"/>with Members, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore concludes, <hi>I charge
thee to keep this Commandment;</hi> that is, that which he all along in the
Epiſtle directed and preſſed with ſo weighty Arguments: As if he had
ſaid, <hi>It is your indiſpenſible Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be careful in this,
becauſe,</hi> as 'tis expreſs'd verſ. 15, 16. <hi>In his own time he
ſhall ſhew who is the bleſſed and onely Potentate,</hi> &amp;c. Jeſus
Chriſt hath given Goſpel-VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to his Church, as King of his Church:
The Potentates of the VVorld ſhew their power in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then in
keeping thoſe who are employed by them to the ſtrict Obſervation of the
Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions given to them; So that if an Embaſſador goes beyond his
Commiſſion, he forfeits his Head; and therefore if any Thing be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,
or any Particular offered in order to a Treaty, which is not in their
Commiſſion, they uſually anſwer, I have no Commiſſion to 
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61819:43"/>anſwer or <hi>meddle</hi> with <hi>this</hi> or
<hi>that</hi> point. Now ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Keep the Commandment
blameleſs without Spot:</hi> Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>King of Kings, and Lord
of Lords, the only Potentate,</hi> and in his time he will ſhew it, and
Examine by what Commiſſion from him they have done what they have done and
Practiced, and will ask this great Queſtion, <hi>Who hath Required this at
your hands?</hi> what ſatisfactory anſwer can any man give, if ſuch a
thing be allowed? If you ask a Rule for Baptizing Children, may not ſuch a
Perſon Demand where your Rule is for Unbabtized Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to Receive the
Lords Supper? If you ask a Rule for ſigning with the Croſs in Baptiſm, he
will ask where your Rule is for Baptizing of Children, and in a word if any one
thing be admitted in point of Practice, that has not the expreſs Warrant of
Gods Word, it will make way for others, becauſe the <pb n="57" facs="tcp:61819:43"/>ſame Reaſon or Pretence that Eſtabliſhes one, may equally be
Produced for another, and another, without end; and ſo a Deviation from Rule
in any thing, though never ſo ſmall, tends directly to bring in the
Inventions and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Men into the Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>From the whole of what hath been ſaid, we may Infer theſe
Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollaries or Inferences,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God hath Preſcribed a particular way and method in
which he will be Worſhiped.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he is ſo tender and nice therein, that the leaſt
Variation from his own Stated Order will not be allowed by him, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
by the puniſhment of ſuch as Tranſgreſſed, and the praiſes given to
ſuch as kept his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as they were Delivered unto them, mentioned at
large before.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That to ſwerve from the Lords Inſtitutions, and Invert
his Order,<pb n="58" facs="tcp:61819:44"/>has a direct Tendency to Deſtroy all Modes of
Worſhip, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently all the publick and ſolemn Exerciſe of
Religion, in as much as the ſame Reaſon by which one Ordinance may be
changed, or Diſcontinued, will equally prove the change or Diſcontinuance
of any, yea of all at long Run.</p>
            <p>And if the firſt Churches might not be Conſtituted without this
Ordinance of Baptiſm, neither may thoſe that ſucceed them, becauſe the
ſame Reaſon that made Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm neceſſary to them, makes it alſo
neceſſary to us. For Goſpel Order ſetled by Apoſtical Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and
Direction, as this was, hath not loſt any of its native worth and efficacy,
or obliging Vertue, by any Diſuſe or Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance occaſioned by any,
but ought to be the ſame to us now, as it was to them in the begining of
ſuch Order; eſpecially conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the day wherein we live, 
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61819:44"/>many indeavouring to bring in their own Inventions into the
Worſhip of God, which ſhould make all Chriſtians be more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and
Zealous to Cleave to the Inſtitutions of Jeſus Chriſt, as they were
firſt Delivered by the holy Penmen, and the Practice of the Primitive
Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>To conclude this head, as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is not to be Repeated,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the Sacrament of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, Initiation, and
Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, which are not capable of Reiteration, ſo neither can the Seal
and Sign thereof; ſo whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever makes for the not Repeating it in the
ordinary uſe of it, makes alſo for this as fully or more, that it ſhould
be the firſt.</p>
            <p>If it not to be repeated becauſe it is the Sign or Seal of
Initiation, Regeneration and Incorporation, by the ſame Reaſon it muſt be
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61819:45"/>firſt, as Initiation, Admiſſion, Incorporation, and
Regeneration, are the firſt Internal Acts in us, and upon us, by which we are
made Chriſtians. But of this we have ſaid enough before.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:61819:45"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV. Shewing that this Opinion that Unbaptized Perſons may
be Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Lords Supper, is againſt the Practice of all
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in all Ages that have Owned Ordinances.</head>
            <p>AS for the Practice of Goſpel times, it hath been evidently
Demonſtrated, that the Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt, did
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly Baptize ſuch as were Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and that after they were
Taught, the next thing was to Baptize them, neither durſt they break that
<hi>order,</hi> the Scripture Rule being, <hi>Teach all Nations, and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize
them; Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Make Diſciples, and Baptize. Mark.</hi> 16.16.
<hi>He that beleiveth and is Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, ſhall be Saved</hi>—You ſee
here the rank of Baptiſm immediately;<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61819:46"/>After Teaching,
after Beleiving, It holds the firſt place of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces properly
Chriſtian: Ye may ſee it again, in the Rule in <hi>Peters</hi> Preaching, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38.</note>
               <hi>Repent and be
Baptized,</hi> which was inſtantly put in Pract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice, which is a ſecond head
of Proof—namely Scripture Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for <hi>they that gladly Received his
Word were</hi> preſently <hi>Baptized, to the Number of</hi> 3000. ver. 41.
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which they <hi>continued</hi> conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly—in Chriſtian
Fellowſhip; and in the Practice of Ordinances, as the Lords Supper, Prayer,
&amp;c. ver. 42. In the Example of the <hi>Eunuch</hi> you have the ſame, as
ſoon as ever Jeſus was Preach'd, and he Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered water, <hi>what
hinders me,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to be Baptized? Nothing,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Philip, if thou haſt Faith,</hi> ſo he was inſtantly
Baptized<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38. &amp; 10.48.</note>—The
like ye have of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> who upon the firſt Preaching of Chriſt,
before the Aſſembly was Baptized he and his.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:61819:46"/>The like you have of the Jaylor <hi>Act.</hi>
16. To whom at Midnight (being aſtoniſhed by a Miraculous <hi>Action</hi>)
the word was Preacht, and to all in his houſe, and he and all his Beleiving,
were forthwith all of them Baptized. Here was no loſs of time, and for the
Order, it was after Faith, and before any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Adminiſtration—There
may be other Inſtances given, but from theſe and the foregoing Pages, this
Concluſion neceſſarily follows, That <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in point of order
and time, is the very next Ordinance to Beleiving. Not but that there ought to
be fit time allowed for the Tryal of Faith, wherein to be ſure the Apoſtles
were not Negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, as being an abſolute Duty.</p>
            <p>As it is certain that in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Goſpel or
whatſoever Relation we have in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, as to matter of Fact or
Precepts, in matter of Right, Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Order and Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61819:47"/>of Baptiſm, do cleerly hold forth the Order to be after
Faith, and the ſubject Baptized by immediate and neceſſary
Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, an Actual Beleiver; So on the other hand it is evident, that
there is not the leaſt Tittle either in expreſs Terms, or Rational and
plain Inference, in the whole new Teſtament, to Countenance the Opinion we
oppoſe. 1. There is no Precept directly or Conſequenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Commanding Us
to Receive any Member without, 2. Nor one Inſtance to be produced, that ever
it was done. 3. It is evident, that the Abettors or Promoters of ſuch a
Practice now, do in ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Gods Order, and lay a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
Foundation for the Abolition of this great and ſacred Inſtitution of our
Chriſtian Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>As for the Ages next the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, for near 300 Years, we have
Examined the Records of thoſe times, and find that the Ordinance 
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61819:47"/>of Baptiſm was Retained by the Churches in the ſame
Order and Mode of Adminiſtration as is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the New Teſtament
<hi>viz</hi> firſt they Taught and Preacht the Goſpel, then they Baptized
all ſuch as were ſo Taught, and ſo immediately Received them into the
Communion of the Church.</p>
            <p>As to the Practice of the ſecond Century we have a memorable
Inſtance In <hi>Juſtin</hi> Martyrs ſecond Apology to <hi>Autoninus
Pius</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> Renders it in his
Saints Reſt, Chap. 8. Sect 5. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'I will declare unto you how we offer up our
ſelves to God after that we are Renewed through Chriſt, thoſe amongſt
us that are <hi>Inſtructed in the Faith</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiue</hi> that which
we teach is true being willing to live according to the ſame, we do
admoniſh to Faſt and Pray for the Forgiveneſs of Sins, and we alſo
Faſt and <pb n="66" facs="tcp:61819:48"/>Pray with them and when they are brought by us
unto the water and there as we were <hi>NEW BORN (that is Baptized)</hi> are
they alſo by <hi>New Birth (viz Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm)</hi> Renewed; and then calling
upon God the Father, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the holy Spirit they
are <hi>waſhed (that is Baptized)</hi> in water. Then we bring the perſon
thus <hi>waſhed</hi> and Inſtructed to the Brethren (as they are called,)
where the Aſſemblies are, that we may pray both for our ſelves, and the
new Illuminated, that we may be found by true Doctrine and by good Works worthy
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers and keepers of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and that we may attain Eternal
Life and Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Then Bread and Wine being brought to the Chief Brother
(ſo they call the Chief Miniſter) he taketh it and offereth praiſe and
Thanksgiving to the Father, by<pb n="67" facs="tcp:61819:48"/>the Name of the Son and Holy
Spirit, and ſo a while he Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brateth Thanksgiving. After Prayer and
Thanksgiving, the whole Aſſembly ſaith, Amen.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'Thanksgiving being ended by the Preſident (or
Chief Guide) and the Conſent of the whole People the Deacons, as we Call
them, do give unto every one Preſent part of the Bread and Wine, over which
Thanks was given, and they alſo ſuffer them to bring it to the
abſent.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'This Food we call the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, to which <hi>NO
MAN</hi> is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but only he that Believeth in the Truth of the Doctrine,
being <hi>waſhed in the Laver of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation</hi> for Remiſſion of
Sins, and that ſo liveth as Chriſt hath Taught.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'So far this Learned Father and Martyr gives a
poſitive account of matter of Fact in his time, from whom we may plainly be 
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61819:49"/>inform'd that no Unbaptized Perſon was then admitted to
the Lords Supper.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> in his Primitive Chriſtianity
pag. 296. part, 1. Chap. 10. 3. Edition Printed 1676. Says thus, Our Lord
having Inſtituted <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> as the two
great Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Chriſtian Law, they have accordingly been ever
acc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted principal parts of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip in the Chriſtian
Church;—<hi>Baptiſm</hi> is the <hi>Door,</hi> by which Perſons Enter
in, and the great and <hi>Solemn</hi> Rite of our Initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation into the Faith of
Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'The Perſons by whom this Sacrament was
Adminiſtred, were the Miniſters of the Goſpel, the Stewards of the
Miſteries of Chriſt, Baptizing and Preaching the Goſpel, being Joyned
toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by our Saviour in the ſame Commiſſion <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'Nor was it accounted enough<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61819:49"/>by
ſome in theſe times that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm was conferred by a Perſon called to
the Miniſtry, unleſs he was alſo <hi>Orthodox</hi> in the
Faith—Hence ſprang that famous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy between <hi>Cyprian</hi>
and <hi>Stephen</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Rebaptizing
thoſe that had been Baptized by <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Cyprian</hi> aſſerting
that they ought to be Rebaptized, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Councel at
<hi>Carthage</hi> of 87. <hi>Affrican</hi> Biſhops, who all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded for
his Opinion—For they looked upon that Baptiſm that had been conferred
by <hi>Hereticks,</hi> as null and invalid, (ſeing <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> being
out of the Church, could not give what they <hi>had</hi> not) and therefore
when they Returned to the Union of the Church, they could not proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be
ſaid to be Rebaptized, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they did but Receive what <hi>(lawfully)</hi>
they had not before <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:61819:50"/> 
               <q rend="inline">'Then page 305. After he had Diſcourſed of
Infant Baptiſm, adds that thoſe who made up the main Body of the Baptized
in thoſe days were <hi>Adult</hi> Perſons, who flocking over daily to the
Faith of Chriſt, were Received in at this <hi>Door.</hi> Uſually they were
for ſome conſiderable time Catechi'sd and Train'd up in the Principle of
the Chriſtian Faith, till having given Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Proficiency in
know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge—and of a ſober and Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Converſation, they then
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>became <hi>Candidates</hi> for Baptiſm, and were accordingly taken in
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'Page 308. Perſons finding themſelves at any
time ſurprized with a dangerous or mortal ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and not daring to
paſs into another World without this Badge of their Initiation into Chriſt,
they preſently ſignified their earneſt deſire to be Baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:61819:50"/>which was done according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as well as the Circumſtances
of a ſick Bed would permit. Theſe were called <hi>Clinici</hi> of (whom
there is frequent mention in the Antient Writers of the Church) becauſe 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>Baptized as they lay along in their Beds. This was
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a leſs Solemn and perfect kind of Baptiſm, partly becauſe
'twas not done by <hi>Immerſion,</hi> but by Sprinkling
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'Page. 333. The Perſons Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating at this
Sacrament (<hi>viz.</hi> the Lords Supper) were at firſt the whole Church or
Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſtians within ſuch a ſpace, that had Embraced the Doctrine
of the Goſpel, and been Baptized into the Faith of Chriſt, uſed
conſtantly to meet together at the Lords Table. As Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Multiply'd,
and a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Diſcipline became neceſſary <hi>NONE</hi> were admitted
to this Ordinance, till they had arrived<pb n="72" facs="tcp:61819:51"/>at the Degree of
the faithful, for who ever were in the State of the <hi>Catechumens</hi> under
Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in order to their Baptiſm, or by Reaſon of any Heinous Crime
under the <hi>Cenſures</hi> and ſuspenſion of the Church, and not yet
paſſed through the ſeveral Stages of the Penitents, <hi>might not
Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate,</hi> and were therefore commanded to <hi>Depart</hi> the
Church, when the reſt went to the Celebration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So far this Learned enquirer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and writer of <hi>Primitive</hi>
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, from whom we may po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively infer that no Unbaptized
perſon was by the Ancients ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Communion of the Lords
Supper.</p>
            <p>It is true that about the third Century, from a fatal miſtake of
<hi>John</hi> 3.5. <hi>Except a man be born of water and of the Spirit, he
can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:61819:51"/>Some began to bring in Infant Baptiſm,
conceiving (as <hi>Cyprian</hi> and his Diſciples taught them) that no
perſon, ſmall or great could be ſaved without it, and that it blotted out
all ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted before its Adminiſtration. Hence <hi>Nazianzen</hi>
exhorts againſt Infant Baptiſm, unleſs in caſe of apparent danger of
Death. When this diſmal Error once took place, how many <hi>miſchiefs</hi>
did follow it, as</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Subjects of Baptiſm were changed from actual
Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to ignorant Babes, and the Church altered in its Primitive
Conſtitution, <hi>viz.</hi> from perſons profeſſing the Faith, to a
mixture of both Converted and Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted ones.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It being conceived that the old manner of Adminiſtration
by Dipping, might be dangerous to Young Infants, and to the people that
Superſtitiouſly delayed their Baptiſm until their Death Bed 
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61819:52"/>(becauſe they believed it would take away all ſin)
therefore they contrived Sprinkling to ſerve the turn for the Infant, as well
as thoſe ſick people, which were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Clinici,</hi> from the Beds or
Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocks they lay in; upon which Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> writes thus: 
<q rend="inline">'He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trays the Church to a diſordered error, if
he cleave not to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, to Dip the Infant in Water, and this I
ſo averr as thinking it (<hi>viz.</hi> Dipping) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding material to the
Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. and no ſlight thing, yea which both Antiquity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly and
without exception of Countrys Hot or Cold, witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes unto, and
eſpecially the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant word of the Holy Ghoſt, firſt and laſt
approveth, as <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabon</hi> in <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. hath noted,
<hi>&amp;c. Treat. of Sacram.</hi> p. 77.</q> which miſadminiſtration came
in time to be decreed by Counſels, and impoſed by fierce and ſevere 
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:61819:52"/>Anathema's, which is all the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that can be
produc'd (and which is indeed nothing at all to us that ought to have Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
Warrant for Practical Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.)</p>
            <p>Now as the Conſequences of this error have been ſo fatal to the
Church of Chriſt, and as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency of it was gradual, ſo 
<note n="*" place="margin">Yet ſo forceable was <hi>Truth</hi> that
they kept the Order tho they miſt the Subject.</note> it ought to be a very
ſerious war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to us, to oppoſe all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginings of error, that is
<hi>to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend earneſtly for the Faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi>
becauſe when error is once admitted, it comes with a fair and ſpecious Mask
of Vizard on, to diſguiſe its deformity, till it ſpreads like a Gangrene,
and infects the whole.</p>
            <p>So this Opinion comes diſguiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the plauſible Allegation
of Charity and Brotherly love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:61819:53"/>But was not the ſame pretence mainly made
uſe of for the intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Infant Baptiſm, <hi>viz.</hi> Charity to the
Childrens Souls, whom they judged in a ſtate of Damnation without it, and
cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly of the two, the introducers of Paedo-Baptiſm are more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable
than the bringers in of this Opinion, becauſe, although they miſt the Right
Subject of Baptiſm, and attributed too much to it, yet they kept up a
Practiſe of that name in its due Rank and Order in the Church, whereas
theſe, on the other hand diſpenſe with the total neglect of Baptiſm,
ſince Baptiſm in Infancy is by them held for no Baptiſm for
unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable Reaſons, as for inſtance. In Baptiſm the Covenant
ſtruck between God and us implies, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the conſent of parties,
but by Infant Baptiſm the Infant is not bound, for he conſented not. Again,
conſent muſt be expreſt, <pb n="77" facs="tcp:61819:53"/>but the Child wants the
juſt ripeneſs and formation of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans inward and outward for ſuch
expreſſions, and ſo cannot will it, becauſe he cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it,
nor can he expreſs that which within him he hath not: Nor can he depute
others to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent for him, nor is there any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for ſuch a
Deputation given by God, nor any Inſtance in the Sacred Records that it was
ever Practiſed. Nor can ſuch as undertake it, perform what they promiſe
for the Child, <hi>viz.</hi> Faith and Repentance, being the two great Graces
of the Goſpel, and the ſole Gift of God. Beſides Chriſt looks for a
Believer, which no Infant can at preſent be ſaid to be, the want of which,
makes the Baptiſm null, for if there be no Bond, no Covenant, no Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
in it (as 'tis plain there is not, and they confeſs it) than there is no
Sealing, for a Seal<pb n="78" facs="tcp:61819:54"/>ſerves but to Ratifie and Confirm a
Bond and Covenant, and as there is no Sealing, ſo there is no exhibition or
conveyance of any thing from Chriſt, for there are no Pipes to receive it,
that is, as an Ordinance, there is no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the uſe of it, no Faith,
no Senſe, no Receptive Faculty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the Ordinance in the manner
of Conveying it <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that the Concluſion is, that Infant
Baptiſm is as much a nullity as the Marrying or Ordination of Infants, and
being really ſo by the grant of the Favourers of this Opinion: it will
unavoidably follow that their admitting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, upon pretence of that
Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm to the Lords Supper, is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more nor leſs, than an
admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without Baptiſm, and a plain Declaration that they eſteem
this Ordinance to be unneceſſary, and conſequently a direct throwing it
out of the Church as was ſaid<pb n="79" facs="tcp:61819:54"/>before, ſo that
<hi>Paedo-Baptiſm</hi> is but a perverting or an abuſe of the Ordinance of
Baptiſm, but this Opinion quite aboliſhes it, which is the neceſſary
effect and Conſequence of their declaring it to be needleſs in order to
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into a Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to Return we can have no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Inſtances of the practice of
An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, then what we find Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the <hi>Cathecumeni,</hi> who were
excluded not only from the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt,</hi> but from the very Sight
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and therefore after the Words <hi>Holy things to Saints,</hi> they
went out, not becauſe they were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Faith, for there were two
ſorts,<hi>viz.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sancta Sanctis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Audien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petentes,
or Electi.</hi>
               </note>Hearers, and ſuch as were competent or Elect; the
firſt were Beginners which heard Sermons, and had a deſire to Chriſt; the
other were ſuch as deſired Baptiſme, and had given up their Names for it,
as 
<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. <hi>de cura pro mortuis.</hi> c.
12.</note>
               <hi>Austin</hi> and others mention.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:61819:55"/>Now theſe were ſuppoſed to have Faith, and
waited only a fit time for the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm, during which time
they were not at all admitted to the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> though judged
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, but as ſoon as Baptized, they were admitted to the <hi>Lords
Supper</hi> on the ſame day alſo.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:61819:55"/> 
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div type="abstract">
                        <head>To Illuſtrate this point further we will give a Brief
Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract of ſome things Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in that Excellent Hiſtory compiled by
the Divines of <hi>Magdeburg.</hi>
                           <note n="*" place="margin">
                              <hi>Cent.</hi> 4.
cap. 6. p 233. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap> Printed
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <hi>Baſil.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                                    <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </hi>
                           </note>
                        </head>
                        <div n="Latin" type="version">
                           <p>
                              <hi>BAſilius non alios quam Cathecumenos Baptizatos
eſſe ſcribit qui in Paſchate convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabantur, Exhort. ad
Baptiſmum.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Baptiſandi au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem in Aſiaticis Eccleſiis, prius
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquandiu in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina Pietatis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rudiebantur, &amp; Cathecumeni di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebantur:
quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum<pb n="82" facs="tcp:61819:56"/>ex</hi> Baſilio <hi>Paulo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
Retulimus.</hi> 
                              <q rend="inline">'<hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectionis</hi> (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit)
<hi>gratiam in die Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis excipiamus. Quamobrem Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleiſia ſuos
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul alta voce convocet Alum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos: ut quos pravum peperit, tunc demum lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
ſanae eruditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis ſide</hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumenos <hi>Enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritos cibi firmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oris
deguſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                       <desc>•…</desc>
                                    </gap>tione Inſtituto<expan>
                                       <am>
                                          <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                       </am>
                                       <ex>que</ex>
                                    </expan>
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto corroboret.</hi>
                              </q> 
                              <hi>Et ibidem rurſus,</hi> 
                              <q rend="inline">'<hi>ſciendum eſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, quod
pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum docere &amp; inſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                       <desc>•…</desc>
                                    </gap>e
oportet; <pb n="83" facs="tcp:61819:56"/>atque ita Deum preclariſſimo bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmate
rite In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe Dignari.</hi>
                              </q>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Narrat Idem</hi> Athanaſius <hi>de</hi> Judaeis, 
<q rend="inline">'<hi>quod ad Epiſcopt ejus ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis</hi>
Genua <hi>ad voluti, Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Petierunt: quos ipſe cum Clericis ſuis
ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiens, perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es plurimos in Doctrina Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianae Pietatis
crudierit; Et Catechumenos inde factos, poſt tridui Jejuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um
Baptizarit.</hi>
                              </q>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div n="English" type="version">
                           <p>
                              <hi>Baſil</hi> Writes, That there were no others but
<hi>Catechumens.</hi> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> Baptized
who were called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
                           <p>Such as were to be Baptized in the Churches of
<hi>Aſia</hi> were firſt for ſome time inſtructed in the Doctrine of
Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and were <pb n="82" facs="tcp:61819:56"/>called <hi>Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens:</hi> as we have
before recited it from <hi>Baſil.</hi> Let us receive (ſaith he) the grace
of Reſurrection in the day of Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. For that Reaſon the Church
with a loud Voice calls together from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far, thoſe ſhe brings up, that
ſuch as were brought forth naught, may at length by the Milk of ſound
Doctrine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> nouriſhed by Faith, be ſtrengthned by
the taſt of more<pb n="83" facs="tcp:61819:56"/>more ſolid food; &amp; perfect
Inſtitution. And there again, we muſt know (ſays he) that it is
neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, firſt to teach and inſtruct, and afterwards dignifie (or
vouchſafe to) him that is ſo right<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Inſtructed, with the moſt
excellent Baptiſme.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Athanaſius</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, the ſame thing of the
<hi>Jews,</hi> that they caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at the feet of the Biſhop of
that City (<hi>v.</hi> where they lived) and deſired Baptiſme, whom when he
and his Clergy beheld, he inſtructed them for many days in the Doctrine of
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Piety and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby made Catechumens after three days Faſt
he Baptized them.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:61819:57"/>This practice of Catechiſing, and then
Baptizing, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards receiving into Church-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip was ſo
Univerſal among all the Chriſtians of thoſe times, as appears by thoſe
few Inſtances, and many more cited from <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius, Nazianzen, Optatus
Milevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus, Epiphanius, Hillarius, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Jerome, Sozomen</hi> and
others, that we find no Oppoſition at all to it; all Candidates for
Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity being that way <hi>only</hi> admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; the neceſſity of it
being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted ſo great, that it became the very inlet of
<hi>Poedo-baptiſm.</hi> So that the Concluſion is undoubted that we have
got above Four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Years of Primitive Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to Witneſs our
practiſe.</p>
            <p>And in the Fifth Century <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> gives the Senſe of
that Age thus. 
<q rend="inline">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tranſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ant per Mare Rubrum,</hi> i.e. <hi>bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zentu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; manducent Manna, id eſt,
Corpus, &amp; Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</hi> Tract. 11. <hi>in</hi> Joh.</note>'Let
them (that is the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecumens</hi>) paſt through the <hi>Red-Sea,</hi>
that is, be baptized, and let them eat <hi>Manna,</hi> that is the Body
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:61819:57"/>and Blood of the Lord.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in the Seventh Century, <hi>Iſidorus de Officiis</hi> makes
Three De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. The Firſt is, 
<q rend="inline">'Of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecumens,</hi> who were ſuch as
were firſt come from <hi>Gentiliſm,</hi> and had a mind to believe in
Chriſt. The Second of <hi>Competents,</hi> who deſire <hi>Baptiſm,</hi>
when they were inſtructed in the Doctrine of Chriſt. And the Third, of the
<hi>Baptized,</hi> who were then Church-Members.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haymo</hi> ſays, in Century Nine,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> cap. 1. <hi>ad</hi> Epheſ. <hi>Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meni ſunt
fideles quia credunt in verum De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um; ſed quia non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zati, non ſunt
Sancti.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q rend="inline">'That the <hi>Catechumes</hi> are the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
becauſe they Believe in the true God; but becauſe they are not Baptized,
they are not Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But what needs any more of theſe Quotations, when all that know
any thing of the practiſe of Antiquity muſt confeſs, That this Opinion we
oppoſe, was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in the World for Sixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years and more. For
though<pb n="86" facs="tcp:61819:58"/>an Antichriſtian Darkneſs over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread the
greateſt part of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom for a long time, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Baptiſm
almoſt crouded that true and Apoſtolical practiſe of Believers Baptiſm
out of the Church; though <hi>Lodovicus Vives</hi> ſays, 
<q rend="inline">'That the cuſtome of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing Adult Perſons
was yearly practis'd in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, even in his time.</q> Yet he
very <hi>Papiſts</hi> all along (as they do at this time) retained this as
the initiating Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; All their Writings Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Decrees,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> cry up Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, to be not only neceſſary to
Church-Communion, but even to Salvation.</p>
            <p>Yea all the Reformers, whether <hi>Lutherans, Calviniſts</hi> or
other For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, The Church of <hi>England,</hi> and all the Diſſenting
Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that own Ordinances (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a few Perſons of the Baptized way and
that lately too) have owned, and do own, That Baptiſm is <pb n="89" facs="tcp:61819:58"/>an Ordinance of Chriſt; yea, the very firſt, or initiating
Ordinance into Church-Fellowſhip, without which, no man may be regularly
admitted to the Supper.</p>
            <p>So that this Opinion is not only againſt us, but contradictory to
the Judgment and Practiſe of all other Chriſtians, Ancient and Modern.
Batiſm was of old, and not without Reaſon, called <hi>The Gate of
Sacraments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Janua Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
               </note> and
is to keep that Name and Nature ſtill, <hi>viz.</hi> to be the firſt and
Primitive Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. If the timing and order of Inſtituted Worſhip be any
thing, as it is of great moment, a great part of it lying in nothing elſe,
but the right and orderly Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Ceremonies, and if the Scripture
Rule and Example be any thing, (which is all we have to ſhew for any
Practiſe,) than Baptiſm is to be the firſt Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance after
Believing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:61819:59"/>If the Teſtimony of Ancient<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Records, and
Modern Writers of all ſorts, unanimouſly makes out that there has not been
any other Practiſe in Fact among Chriſtians all along, than what we here
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, though that is not brought by it ſelf to prove the ſame, it
is certainly a very fair Collateral in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orcement and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration: For there is no point of Religion
debated in the World, that has a more clear and Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal concurrence of
ſixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dread years compleat, than, that no perſons were received to
the Communion of the Lords Supper or Church-Fellowſhip, unleſs they were
firſt Baptiſed. Yea ſuch a value had Antiquity for this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, that
ſuch as were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed by Hereticks, as the <hi>Arians</hi> and others,
that uſed not the name of Chriſt, or (otherwiſe) defectively performed
it, were judged by the moſt Learned men <pb n="89" facs="tcp:61819:59"/>of their times to
be Unbaptized, and therefore were Baptiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain by ſuch as were Orthodox,
when they left their Hereſies, which is ſo well known that it needs no
inſtances,</p>
            <p>To conclude this Chapter, we ſhall give a few inſtances of
ſome Modern Writers beſides what are given before, not ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving
Authority from them, (though they deſerve all due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect) but becauſe
of the ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity and force of their Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</p>
            <p>A very noted and Learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor now living, writes thus, (1.) 
<q rend="inline">'If we have neither Precept nor Example in Scripture
ſince Chriſt Ordained Baptiſm, of any other way of Admitting Viſible
Members, but only by Baptiſm, than all that muſt be admitted Viſible
Members; muſt be ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily Baptiſed: But ſince Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm was
Inſtituted (or Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed<pb n="92" facs="tcp:61819:60"/>we have no Precept or
Example of admitting Viſible Members any other way (but 
<note n="*" place="margin">John 4.1. Act. 2.38,41. &amp;
8.12,13,16,36,38. &amp; 9.18. &amp; 10.47,48. &amp; 16.15,33. &amp; 18.8. &amp;
19.3,4,5. Rom. 6.3. &amp;c.</note> conſtant Precept and Example of admitting
this way:) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all that muſt be admitted Viſible Members, muſt be
Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'I know not what in any ſhew of Reaſon can be
ſaid to this by thoſe that renounce not Scripture. For what man dare go in
a way which hath neither Precept nor Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to warrant it, from a Way that
hath a full Current of both? yet they that will admit Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers into the
Viſible Church without Baptiſm, do ſo.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2"> 
               <q rend="inline">2. 'Either Members muſt be Baptized at their
Admiſſion or elſe after they are ſtated in the Church, or elſe never.
But the two later are falſe: therefore it muſt be the former way,
<hi>viz.</hi> at their admiſſion.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1"> 
               <q rend="inline">(1.) 'That they ſhould never<pb n="93" facs="tcp:61819:60"/>be
Baptiſed, none will affirm but the Seekers, and they that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
Ordinances (that is, above obedience to God, and ſo Gods.)</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2"> 
               <q rend="inline">(2.) 'If they ſay they muſt be Baptiſed after
they are ſtated in the Church (and that many years as they would have it) I
anſwer (1.) Shew any Scripture for that if you can. (2.) It is contrary to
all Scripture Example, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. The three thouſand were preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Baptiſed, and the Jaylor at the ſame hour of the night, and ſo of all the
reſt. And if you could ſhew any that did delay it, (ſince Chriſts
Command, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20.) It would appear to have been ſinful, as
through Ignorance or Negligence; ſo that then it muſt needs be done at
their firſt Admittance according to the conſtant courſe of
Scripture.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3"> 
               <q rend="inline">3. 'It is evident alſo from the very Nature and
end of Baptiſm, which is to be Chriſts Liſting and<pb n="92" facs="tcp:61819:61"/>Ingaging Sign; and therefore muſt be applyed when we enter his
Army.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="4"> 
               <q rend="inline">4. 'If we were (Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Baptiſed into one Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, then we are not to delay it till
we are ſtated in the Body: But we are all Baptiſed into one Body, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 12 13. therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For if it be the uſe of
Baptiſm to ingraft and enter us into the Body or Church (and into Chriſt,
as <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3.) than ſure it muſt be uſed as our ingrafting and
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance. Shall a Souldier be Liſted two or three years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath been
in the Army, or at the firſt entrance, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</q>
            </p>
            <p n="5"> 
               <q rend="inline">(5.) 'If all Church Members are Chriſts
Diſciples, and all Diſciples muſt be Baptiſed (at their Admiſſion)
then all Church-Members muſt be Baptiſed at their Admiſſion: but all
Church-Members are Diſciples, and all<pb n="93" facs="tcp:61819:61"/>Diſciples muſt
be Baptiſed at their Admiſſion, therefore all Church-Members muſt be
Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed at their Admiſſion.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">1. 'That Diſciples muſt be Baptiſed at their
Admiſſion is plain, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19,20. <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple all Nations
Baptiſing them,</hi> and by conſtant Example (2.) That all Church-Members
are Diſciples I prove thus, (1.) If it be the Church which is Chriſts
School, than all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church are his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars or Diſciples,
or Members of his School: but it is only the Church which is called Chriſts
School; therefore all Church-Members are School-Members or Diſciples, (2.)
And thus if all Church-Members are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and all Chriſtians are
Chriſts Diſciples, then all Church-Members are Chriſts Diſciples: but
all Church-Members are Chriſtians, and all Chriſtians<pb n="96" facs="tcp:61819:62"/>are Chriſts Diſciples: therefore all Church-Members are Chriſts
Diſciples, (1.) That all Church-Members (true ones) are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that
is retainers to Chriſt, or ſuch as belong to Chriſt (as his own Phraſe
is) is beyond doubt, (2.) That all Chriſtians are Diſciples I proved
before, it being the plain words of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.26. The
Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were called Chriſtians firſt at <hi>Antioch;</hi> ſo that
all Church-Members being Diſciples, they muſt regularly be Baptiſed at
their Admiſſion, according to the courſe of Scripture, and my Text,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19,20.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="6"> 
               <q rend="inline">(6) 'Another Argument may be plainly fetcht from
<hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26. <hi>That he might Sanctifie it, and cleanſe it (his
Church) by the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Water through the Word;</hi> If the whole Church
muſt be San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by the waſhing of Water then all particular Members of
the <pb n="97" facs="tcp:61819:62"/>Church muſt be ſo Sanctified! but the whole Church
muſt be ſo Sanctified: therefore the Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Members.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'He further writes thus, From <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19.
<hi>Go and Diſciple me all Nations Baptizing them,</hi> &amp;c. What Chriſt
hath conjoyned, man muſt not ſeparate: Cut Chriſt hath conjoyned
Diſcipling and Captizing, as a ſtanding courſe to the end of the World.
(as the next verſe ſpeaks;) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt not ſeparate them.
Though the Word <hi>[for ever]</hi> do ſometimes ſignifie a limited time in
the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> viz. till the New World under Chriſt; yet in
the Goſpel [till the end of the World can have no other then the proper
Signification without plain Impudent Violence.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2"> 
               <q rend="inline">(2) 'Argument 2. from 1. Cor. 12,13. <hi>By one
Spirit we are all Baptized into one Body.</hi> If Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm be Gods appointed
ordinary <pb n="96" facs="tcp:61819:63"/>way of ingrafting all into the Body of Chriſt,
then it is a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ordinance, as being of a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſe: but
Baptiſm is ſo, therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Antecedent will appear plain
in the Text, if you conſider, Firſt, that it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Baptiſm that is
here mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; the Spirit being ſpoken of as a concurrent cauſe;
Secondly, That it was <hi>All</hi> that were thus baptized into the
body.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3"> 
               <q rend="inline">(3) 'From <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. If the uſe of
Baptiſm be to baptiſe Men into Jeſus Chriſt, and into his Death, then
it is a ſtanding Ordinance to the Church, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a ſtanding uſe:
but the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is in the Text, therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="4"> 
               <q rend="inline">4. 'From <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. &amp; 22.16. If
Baptiſm be Inſtituted for the Remiſſion of ſin, or the Waſhing away
of ſin (whether by ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Sealing or exhibiting) then it is a
ſtanding Ordinance to the Church; (as being to a<pb n="97" facs="tcp:61819:63"/>ſtanding Uſe and End, one Age of the Church having no leſs need
of it then another.) But the Antecedent is in the Text; therefore,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="5"> 
               <q rend="inline">5. 'If the End of Baptiſm be our Burial and
Reſurrection with Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. The Churches Salvation, 1
<hi>Pet.</hi> 3,21. If a Foundation Principle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. The Ordinary
way of Initiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or putting on Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. Then it is of
continual uſe, and ſo a ſtanding Ordinance: but it is ſo, as the Texts
cited ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſay; therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="6"> 
               <q rend="inline">6. 'If Chriſt himſelf has In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted the
Ordinance of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm in the Word, and not again Repealed it; then it is a
ſtanding Ordinance to the Church; (and no man muſt dare to Repeal his Laws)
but Chriſt hath Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted; and let any man ſhew where he hath Repealed
it that can; and till then it muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged<pb n="98" facs="tcp:61819:64"/>to be
ſtill in force.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Learned and Reverend Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> in his <hi>Marrow of
Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> page 181. ſays, 
<q rend="inline">'Baptiſm is the Sacrament of Initiation or
Regeneration, repreſenting and confirming our very ingrafting into Chriſt,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3,5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. and p. 182. Baptiſm is but once
to be Adminiſtred, becauſe there is but one begining of Spiritual Life by
Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as there is but one begining of Natural Life by
Generation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul Bayne,</hi> that Holy Learned man, on <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11.
<hi>page</hi> 280. ſaith, 
<q rend="inline">'God doth unite us with Chriſt even by our
Baptiſm, that is, ſaith he, the Believer Baptiſed, is by Baptiſm
mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted ſo before the Church.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elton</hi> on the ſame place <hi>p.</hi> 291. 
<q rend="inline">'Baptiſm is the Sacrament of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion or
ingrafting into Chriſt, Sealing up our ſetting into Chriſt, which is only
once, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <pb n="99" facs="tcp:61819:64"/>after to be done again; for if it did not,
then we ſhould have another ingrafting into Chriſt, and afterward
Nouriſhed in him, therefore we often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Ordinance of the Lords
Supper.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> in his Diſcourſe of the Spirit, <hi>pag.</hi>
50. where he proving the Divine Nature, and Perſonality of the Holy Spirit,
thus writes, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sect. 11. 
<q rend="inline">'All things neceſſary to this purpoſe are
compriſed in the ſolemn Form of our initiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into Covenant with God,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt Commands his Apoſtles to
Diſciple all Nations, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing them in the Name of the Father, and the Son,
and the Holy Ghoſt: this is the Foundation we lay of all our Obedience and
Profeſſion, which are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated by this Initial Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:61819:65"/>Sect. 14. <hi>page</hi> 51. Tells us, 
<q rend="inline">'we are Sacredly Initiated or Conſecrated, or
Dedicated unto the Service and Worſhip of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,
this we took upon us in our Baptiſm, herein lyes the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our Faith
and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with that Ingagement of our ſelves unto God, which
Conſtitutes our Chriſtianity. This is the Pledge of our entring into
Covenant with God, and our giving up our ſelves unto him in the Solemn Bond
of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Strong</hi> in his Diſcourſe of the Covenants,
<hi>pag.</hi> 226. Says, 
<q rend="inline">'Baptiſm is a Sacrament of Initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and the
Ordinance of viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Admiſſion into the Church; and that muſt not be
done pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly, and without diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; for as it is a ſin to
keep out thoſe whoſe Right it is, ſo its a ſin alſo to admit them 
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:61819:65"/>that have no Right, becauſe thereby the Ordinances of
Chriſt are abuſed and miſplaced, where he never intended them, and for
whom he never Inſtituted them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>page</hi> 306. 
<q rend="inline">'We are ſaid to be Baptiſed into the Name of
them all (<hi>viz.</hi> Father, Son and Spirit) <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20.
<hi>Baptiſing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy
Ghoſt:</hi> Now what is it to be Baptiſed into the Name of the Father; its
conceived to be taken from the manner of Marriage, wherein the Wife doth
<hi>Tranſire in Nomen, in familiam,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>into the Name and Family
of the Husband:</hi> or of Servants, who had their Maſters name called upon
them: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no man might be Baptiſed in the name of a Creature, it
is that which <hi>Paul</hi> deteſts, that he ſhould Baptiſe in his own 
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:61819:66"/>name; and therefore the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, to be Baptiſed
<hi>in Fidem, in Cultum,</hi> into the Faith and Worſhip of God, and ſo you
are unto them all, and give up your names unto them all; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unto
each perſon we owe both Faith and Worſhip di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, all manner of Duty
and Obedience, becauſe we are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly Baptiſed into the Faith of them
all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Manton</hi> in his Excellent Sermons, on <hi>Pſal.</hi>
119. <hi>ver.</hi> 8- <hi>p.</hi> 45, In the proſecution of his Doctrine,
<hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">'That it is a great advantage to come to a
Reſolution in a courſe of Godlineſs, ſaith that it is a courſe God
will bleſs, he hath appointed Ordinances to this end and purpoſe that we
might come to this Reſolution. The Promiſe is firſt implicitely made in
Baptiſm, therefore it is called, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. the anſwer of a good
Conſcience towards <pb n="103" facs="tcp:61819:66"/>God. How ſo? Why the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
binds mutually on Gods part and on ours; and ſo do the Seals which belong to
the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. It doth not only Seal Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Sanctification on Gods part,
but there is a promiſe and anſwer on our part: an anſwer to what? To the
demands of the Covenant. In the Covenant of Grace, God ſaith I will be your
God, (Baptiſm Seals that) and we promiſe to be his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Now our
Anſwer to this Demand of God, and to this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatory he puts to us in the
Covenant, it is Sealed by us in Baptiſm; and it is Renewed in the Lords
Supper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Burroughs,</hi> on <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.12. Gives us this
obſervation, 
<q rend="inline">'That whatever is urged to us or Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed by us
in matter of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip muſt have warrant out of the written Word of God (it
was ſin) and why? Becauſe I have<pb n="104" facs="tcp:61819:67"/>written to them
(ſaith he) the great things of my Law, and they counted it a ſtrange thing
though that which they did had a great deal of ſeeming Devotion in it, yet it
was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than that which was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Law.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'This Queſtion ſhould be put to any that tender
to us any way of Worſhip or Doctrine of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion under any ſpecious ſhew
whatſoever, where is it written? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>If they ſpeak
not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word, 'tis becauſe they have no light in them.</hi> Oh
they ſeem to be very judicious and wiſe, <hi>But if they ſpeak not
according to the word, its becauſe there is no light in them,</hi> to the
written Law and Teſtimony, that muſt be the ſtandard at which all
Doctrine and ways of Worſhip muſt be tried, many may put fair colours upon
the Way, that it is for Common<pb n="105" facs="tcp:61819:67"/>Peace, and a great deal of
Good may be done by it, and the like. But is it written? <hi>Did I ever command
it ſaith God?</hi> Policy may ſay 'tis fit; Reaſon may ſay 'tis comely;
and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may ſay 'tis uſeful: but what doth the written Word ſay
it ſhould be? Nay it is not enough to ſay that we cannot ſay 'tis
forbidden; but where is it written in matters of Worſhip? This is a certain
Rule, ſaith <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian.</hi> If it be ſaid 'tis Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, becauſe the
Scripture doth not forbid it, it may equally be retorted; it is therefore not
law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, becauſe the Scripture doth not Command it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And further that Reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>p,</hi> 86. Notes from
<hi>Exod.</hi> 39. at leaſt ten times in that Chapter, 
<q rend="inline">'<hi>They did according to what the Lord
commanded</hi> Moſes, and in verſe 43. Moſes <hi>bleſsed the
people.</hi> The people are bleſſed when in<pb n="106" facs="tcp:61819:68"/>the matters
of Worſhip they keep unto what is Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This was the Judgment of that Famous Servant of God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though no
man in his time (as thoſe that knew him in his life can teſtifie) was of a
more ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der and bearing ſpirit to heal Differences then he; yet how Zealous
and Careful was he to adviſe and inculcate into the minds of Chriſtians,
that they ſhould exactly keep to the written Word in matters of Gods
Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Worſhip.</p>
            <p>By what is ſaid (Chriſtian Reader) it evidently appears what a
value all Chriſtians in all Ages, yea at this day have had for this great
Ordinance of Baptiſm, and how Vniverſally Concurrent their Teſtimonies
are, that it is not only the Sacrament of Initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but alſo to be
continued in the Church unto the end of the<pb n="107" facs="tcp:61819:68"/>World. And
becauſe it would ſwell this ſmall piece beyond its intended Bulk to uſe
ſo great a Cloud of Witneſſes, we ſhall add a few General and
Comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Teſtimonies.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the Articles of Religion Publiſhed by His Majeſties
ſpecial Command 1642. Baptiſm is thus Defined. 
<q rend="inline">'Baptiſm is not only a Sign of Profeſſion, and
Mark of difference, whereby Chriſtian men are diſcerned from others that be
not Chriſtned: but it is alſo a ſign of Regeneration or New Birth,
whereby as by an Inſtrument, they that receive Baptiſm rightly are Grafted
into the Church, the promiſes of the forgiveneſs of ſin; and of our
Adoption to be the Sons of God by the Holy Ghoſt, and viſibly Signed and
Sealed: Faith is confirm'd, and Grace increaſed by vertue of Prayer unto God,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> This is the<pb n="108" facs="tcp:61819:69"/>Judgmen of the Church of
<hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'The Aſſembly of Divines in their Confeſſion
of Faith Printed One thouſand ſix hundred fifty eight, <hi>pag.</hi> 94.
Define Baptiſm a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the New Teſtament Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by Jeſus
Chriſt (<hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19.) not only for the ſolemn ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of
the Party baptized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Viſible Church, (1 Cor. 12,13.) <hi>But alſo
to be unto him a Sign and Seal of the Covenant of Grace.</hi> (Col. 2.12.)
<hi>Of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafting into Chriſt.</hi> Gall. 3.17.) <hi>Of
Regeneration.</hi> (Tit. 3.5.) <hi>Of Remiſſion of Sins.</hi> (Mark 1.4.)
And <hi>of his giving up unto God through Jeſus Chriſt, to walk in
Newneſs of Life.</hi> (Rom. 6.3,4.) Which Sacrament is by Chriſts own
Appointment to continue in his Church until the end of the World,
<hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19,20. This is the Judgment of the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi>
ſuitable to which<pb n="109" facs="tcp:61819:69"/>they Expreſs themſelves in their
Larger Catechiſm, <hi>pag.</hi> 128. and in the Shorter Catechiſm,
<hi>page</hi> 157.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'The Congregational, (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called
<hi>Independent</hi>) Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, in their Confeſſion of Faith at the
<hi>Savoy,</hi> where were many of their Elders, <hi>Oct.</hi> 1658. Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
1659.</q> Thus ſay of Baptiſm. Baptiſm <hi>is a Sacrament of the New
Teſtament Ordained by Jeſus Chriſt to be unto the Party baptized a Sign
and Seal of the Covenant of Grace, of his Ingrafting into Chriſt, of
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, of Remiſſion of Sins, and of his giving up unto God through
Jeſus Chriſt to walk in Newneſs of Life; which Ordinance is by Chriſts
own appointment to be continued in his Church until the end of the
World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Churches of hriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (though unjuſtly) called
<hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts:</hi> in their Confeſſion of Faith; (Fourth
Impreſſion Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<pb n="110" facs="tcp:61819:70"/>1652) 
<q rend="inline">'Define Baptiſm an Ordinance of the New
Teſtament given by Chriſt, to be diſpenſed upon Perſons
Profeſſing Faith, or that are made Diſciples; who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Profeſſion of
Faith, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it, ought to be Baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and after to partake of
the Lords Supper.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Objection, <hi>If it ſhould be Objected, To what purpoſe ſerve
all theſe Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations ſince the Parties you diſpute againſt do believe
and hold, That</hi> Baptiſme is an Ordinance of Chriſt and keep up the
Practice of it.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> 1. Although they hold and practiſe it
themſelves, yet in the Effect and Conſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uence of this their Opinion, they deny it: For whilſt they
alleage, That it is not requiſite to Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, it muſt of
neceſſity be underſtood, that they judge it not a requiſite Duty for a
Chriſtian;<pb n="111" facs="tcp:61819:70"/>and conſequently. 'tis needleſs and
therefore may be laid aſide with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger, which is in effect a total
caſting of it away: which is not only contradictory to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, but
diſagreeable to all other Chriſtians in the World, as hath been fully made
out.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If they hold Baptiſm to be a Chriſtian Duty, I would
ask, Whether it be the duty of all Chriſtians, or only ſome? If of All, how
can it be diſpenſed with in any? if only of ſome, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as
are convinced of it; it will equally follow, by the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that no
Ordinance at all, is a Duty to a perſon that doubts ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the thing it
ſelf, or the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or circumſtances of its practiſe And if it be not a
duty, no man may be blamed for the nonperfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it, but indeed would Sin
in doing it, and ſo by conſequence, no Ordinance is binding to all,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is not one of them, but<pb n="211" facs="tcp:61819:71"/>is in ſome
reſpect or other cavill'd at, or at leaſt not rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by
ſome perſons that yet would be eſteemed Godly: ſo that this Opinion
opens a gap, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for Excluſion of Baptiſm, but of any Ordinance
whatſoever, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of a large Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to a doubting Perſon,
that is really Holy, or ſeems ſo to be. But the Lord never left his
Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances upon ſuch termes; For they are not to be diſpen'd with upon any
pretence whatſoever without his own ſpecial Warrant.</p>
            <p>Suitable to what we here Write, <hi>Henry
Lawrence</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> A very Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious and Learned Writer
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes himſelf, in his Book of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, <hi>pag.</hi> 368.
<hi>chap.</hi> 17. thus, that there is an order in the Worſhip of the New
Teſtament: (ſays he) 
<q rend="inline">'No Man will deny that hath Learned with <hi>Paul,
To join be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeng the Order and Faith of Saints,</hi> Coll. 2.5. And now 
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:61819:71"/>will acknowledg this more then they who deny themſelves
of ſome very conſiderable Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for want of coming to them in the
right order, as the Lords Supper for want of Church-Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip: every thing
is ſeaſonable and beautiful in its time, out of which it is diſorderly
and evil, To find the Order and Time of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> will I conceive be
the eaſieſt thing in all this Inquiry, whether you conſider Scripture
Rule, Scripture Example, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Primitive Church, or indeed of all
that ever was, or the reaſon of things; For Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Rule you have
<hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Make Diſciples and Baptiſe.</hi> Mark 16.16.
<hi>He that believeth and is baptiſed ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> You ſee
here the Rank of Baptiſm, immediately after Teaching, after Believing, it
holds the firſt place of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces properly Chriſtian, you may 
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:61819:72"/>ſee it again in the Rule of <hi>Peters</hi> Preaching,
<hi>Acts</hi> 2.38.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'For the Primitive times we can have no better
inſtances, than what we have of the <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chuminy,</hi> who were excluded
not only from the Euchariſt, but from the very ſight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'And of this the Fathers give a Reaſon,
<hi>viz.</hi> In all reſpects the Order of the Miſtery is kept, that
firſt by Remiſſion of ſins, a Medicine be prepared for their Wounds,
and then the Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Heavenly Table be added <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
&amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'If you paſs from Precept and Example of all times
to Reaſon, there you will find that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever makes for the not repeating of
Baptiſm in the ordinary uſe of it, makes alſo for this as fully, or more,
that it ſhould be the firſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:61819:72"/> 
               <q rend="inline">'For, Firſt if it be not to be repeated, becauſe
this is the Seal of Initiation, Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Incorporation, then by the
ſame Reaſon this muſt be firſt as Initiation, Admiſſion,
Incorporation, and Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are the firſt Internal Acts in us, and upon
us, by which we are made Chriſtians.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'Secondly, if the ſignification, and Uſe of
Baptiſm be for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and of conſtant and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Uſe, then this
Ordinance is to lie as the bottom ſtone in which is to have a durable and
conſtant influence into the whole Edifice.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'Thirdly, If this be not to be repeated, becauſe
neither in Precept nor Example you find it ſo, and never otherwiſe, or if
the ends of Baptiſm on our part, be that there ſhall be a formal external
Contract paſt<pb n="116" facs="tcp:61819:73"/>with God, by which we are viſſibly
Handfaſted in this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Marriage Or, 2. To diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh our
ſelves by this Badge and Charecter of our Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the evil
world, which we renounce with all its Works, then certainy this Piece is to be
firſt Adminiſtred before we go further, and the Sacrament of our Spiritual
Life and Birth is to be given before that of our Nouriſhment: in a word
Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm hath been called of old, and not without Reaſon,
<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentorum janua,</hi> and is for all theſe conſiderations, which
are as many as concurr to any one thing to Keep that Name and Nature ſtill,
which is to be the firſt and Primitive Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, in which a Converted
perſon, man or woman, is to Communicate. Now then if the Timing and Order of
Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Worſhip be any thing, as<pb n="117" facs="tcp:61819:73"/>it is of great
moment, a great part of it lying in nothing elſe but the right and Orderly
Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Ceremonies; and if the Scripture Rule and Example be any
thing, which is all we have to ſhow for any Practice; then Baptiſm is to be
the firſt Sacrament after Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving: beſides the reaſon of the thing,
that which makes it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to Baptiſe before Teaching is, becauſe the
Scripture hath ranked it otherwiſe, that ſays Teach and Baptiſe, not
Baptiſe and Teach, as the Papiſts and others do, the ſame Reaſon will
hold for the giving it its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in time to any other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,
becauſe its ranked im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after Teaching, and before any other
thing.</q> Thus far you have the Opinion and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that Learned
Gentleman.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:61819:74"/>
            <head>CHAP. V. Wherein the Objections againſt this Poſition viz.
That none may be Regularly admitted to the Lords Supper, that are not firſt
Baptized, are Anſwered.</head>
            <p>Obj. 1. <hi>THere is no Rule, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Warrant of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to
Exclude Perſons fearing God, from receiving the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, who by vertue
of their Faith have a Right to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Objection ſuppoſes things very dangerous.
As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Holineſs without Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm inveſts a Right to
other Church Ordinances, which is not to be ſuppoſed, for Chriſt the Lamb
of God was Holy in the Higheſt Degree, and in him was<pb n="119" facs="tcp:61819:74"/>found no Sin, yet he was Baptized before he entred upon his Publick
Miniſtry,<note place="margin">Matt. 3.15,16.</note> which is a moſt
Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Example, and the Pattern which the Saints followed; for in a
Word, the great Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> and all thoſe Primitive Saints
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by the Spirit to be Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and therefore Holy; were
nevertheleſs Baptized, which might have been forborn but that it was an
indiſpenſable Duty: and whatſoever Reaſon may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, why Holineſs
without Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm may ſerve, the like may be produced, Why Holineſs
without any other Ordinance may be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for a Believer? And unleſs
it be leſs neceſſary now for Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to perform Goſpel Duties, then
for Evangelical Saints; or unleſs it can be made out, that Baptiſm was only
Appointed for that Age, (as Holy an Age as ever was,) then the obligation of
Practiſing that Duty ſtill lies upon All Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,<pb n="120" facs="tcp:61819:75"/>which is a Warrant and Rule for the Excluſion of ſuch as will not
ſubmit to it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It ſuppoſes, That whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is not forbidden in
Scripture, is Lawful; and ſo the Receiving of Believers that are not baptized
to the Supper, being not Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is therefore Lawful.</p>
            <p>Now that this is a Pernicious way of Argument, has been large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Demonſtrated about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as tending to bring all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Inventions
into Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to which we refer: yet doubtleſs, it will be granted by
all that the only Warrant we have, (as has been frequently ſaid) for the
Practice of Goſpel Duties, muſt be the expreſs Warrant, or Word of God;
according to which we muſt walk: and I very well remember, That the Old
Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts who faithfully follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> according to the
Light they had received, rather than<pb n="121" facs="tcp:61819:75"/>they would kneel at
the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thought it their Duty to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the Practice of that great
Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, giving this as their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: To leave (ſay they) the
Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the manner of Receiving the
Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and to follow the Practice of Men, in a poſture Invented by Men
is not ſafe: but to kneel at the Sacrament is ſo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not ſafe.</p>
            <p>And if the Servants of God in thoſe times were ſo Cautious of
doing any thing that might be an Addition to the Worſhip of God, although but
in a Circumſtance: how much ought Chriſtians Now when the Matter is about
the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Order of the Practiſe of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances themſelves; for here in the
Caſe in hand, is a moſt evident leaving the Practice of Chriſt and his
Apoſtles, and following the Inventions of Men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Commiſſion given by<pb n="122" facs="tcp:61819:76"/>Chriſt
<hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Go teach all Nations Baptizing them, &amp;c.</hi>
hath been an Argument of great weight in the minds of all that oppoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant
Baptiſm; the order of the words ſhewing who are to be baptized,
<hi>viz.</hi> Such as are taught <hi>Firſt Teach, then Baptize:</hi> and if
it be an Argument, that proves Believers baptiſm only, It muſt have its
Conſideration, That Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm muſt go before the Practice of other
Ordinances, as <hi>Preaching</hi> goes before <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We find <hi>Act.</hi> 1.3. that Jeſus Chriſt was Forty days with
his Diſciples, ſpeaking of the things pertaining to the Kingdom of God; and
doubtleſs he was not wanting in giving them dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction concerning the order
of his Worſhip. For as the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. was given
after his Reſurrection, we may ſee his Apoſtles (as appears by their
conſtant Adminiſtrations ſutable<pb n="123" facs="tcp:61819:76"/>thereto) did
Practiſe no other way, as <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41,42. and ſeveral other places
fully produced before. Which Practiſe in order to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving or enjoying
of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I take to be a conſtant and a ſtanding <hi>direction</hi>
for all Churches, in all times, unleſs any can ſhew a variation from it, by
any of the Primitive Churches afterwards, which cannot be done; I would fain
know of him that Preaches the Goſpel to men, what Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine he is to Preach
to them? is it any other than to Believe and be Baptiſed; If no other, (as I
judg all will grant) than if in caſe the party Believing ſhould queſtion
whether Water Baptiſm be the Ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt, or if he believes
it, is not yet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied it is his duty to be Baptiſed, but deſires he
may break Bread with the Church, can this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a manifeſt breach of the
Rule be Admitted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:61819:77"/>The Apoſtle tells us <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27.
<hi>That ſo many of you</hi> (or as ſome render it) <hi>all yee that are
Baptiſed into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt,</hi> that is, they have 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The Verb
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies to put on as a
Garment.</hi> Liegh Crit. Sacr.</note>put on Chriſt as a Garment, and by
Baptiſm have put on the viſible Profeſſion of Chriſt, plainly holding
out, that none have put on the viſible Profeſſion of Chriſt until they
be Baptized; the outward Sign, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering to the inward Grace, ſo
<hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Know ye not that we who were Baptiſed into Jeſus
Chriſt, were Baptiſed into his Death:</hi> which Baptiſm is a pledge
of—Can it therefore be judged upon any Reaſonable pretence that any man
ſhould be Admitted to Walk in the Practiſe of the Ordinances of Chriſt,
before he hath put on Chriſt in the viſible Profeſſion of his Name by
Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>From the whole of which we infer, in anſwer to the Objection That
our Practice ſuitable to theſe<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61819:77"/>Precepts and Examples,
are a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Rule and Warrant for our not admitting them to the Lords
Supper, and to call for Scripture Precepts or Examples for refuſing them, is
very abſurd; For we may as well call for the like to Warrant our Separation
from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> by Name, which can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced no more then
this, yet it does not follow, that Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with that Church, as now it is,
is Lawful. Scripture Examples are matter of Fact; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, there having
been no ſuch corrupt Practice crept into the world when the Scripture was
written, therefore there was no occaſion for any baptized Perſon to
diſclaim Communion with the Unbaptized; there being no ſuch Cauſe of
which to make an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
            <p>Obj. 2. <hi>But we admit none to the Supper of the Lord, but thoſe
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:61819:78"/>that think they are Baptiſed alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and Judg what
they received in their Infancy ſufficient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It is certain that they who believe that the only
Subjects of Baptiſm are actual Believers, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch who upon a
Profeſſion of Faith received that Ordinance, and eſteemed no other
Baptiſm valid, cannot judg the Baptiſm received in Infancy to be Chriſts
Baptiſm, they knowing that the proper Subject appointed by Chriſt,
<hi>viz.</hi> a Believer (which is the main part of the Eſſence of the
Ordinance) is wanting, and certainly the Ground of Churches proceedings, in
admitting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the Supper cannot be built upon the imagination of the
party deſiring Communion, but upon the knowledg the Church hath of it, and
its being tryed by the Rule which they are to Walk by. For,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:61819:78"/>Suppoſe a Perſon deſires to ſit down as
a Member of the Church, as thinking he hath a true Faith, and a Right to the
Priviledge in the Church, when yet he can give no ſatisfactory
demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of either; will any think the Church ought to receive him
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath that good perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of himſelf, when they
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are ſatisfied that what he declares is inſufficient by the
Rule, to make out his Right? Or will any judgment of Charity warrant ſuch a
proceeding? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly no; and yet the Reaſon is the ſame for the latter,
as for the former. Beſides the Conſequence to the party that ſhould be
ſo Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Supper upon his conceit that he is Baptized is very
dangerous, and muſt needs build him up in a conceit that he hath that which
indeed he hath not. God of old gave this charge, that a <hi>ſtumbling-block
muſt not<pb n="128" facs="tcp:61819:79"/>be put in the way of the blind, and</hi>
ſurely a greater ſtumbling-block cannot be put in ſuch mens way to hinder
their inquiry after the True Baptiſm of Chriſt then to admit of that
ſuppoſition, which the Church knoweth is not true. For having now the
enjoyment of all the priviledges of the Houſe of God, they hereby are for
ever careleſs of making any further In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry: and I heartily wiſh that this
may be ſeriouſly conſidered by thoſe that exerciſe this ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
Charity.</p>
            <p>Again, ſuppoſe the Child of a Baptized Perſon of ſufficient
Age, that was brought up in a Godly manner, is Converted and become a Believer,
yet was never Baptized at all, ſhould propoſe for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the
Church, would they admit him without Baptiſm, if he deſires Communion ſo?
(not being ſatisfied, that it is a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Duty,) If they would, then 
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:61819:79"/>it is evident, that they quite Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude Baptiſm out of
the Rank of Ordinances; If they do not admit him, then they place a
ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency in Infant Baptiſm, becauſe they grant a Priviledge to him
that had it, and deny the ſame to him that had it not, (whom we do
ſuppoſe to be as much a Believer, and as holy as the other) which is
expreſly againſt their own Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, <hi>viz.</hi> to eſteem Infant
Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm as no Baptiſm; and therefore if they hold to it, ſhould place
him that was ſo in infancy baptized, and him that was never baptized, in the
ſame rank, with reſpect to the Priviledge of Church Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
            <p>Object. 3. <hi>It is ſaid,</hi> Rom. 14.1. Him that is weak in the
Faith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you, <hi>and it being but the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuch perſons to
judge their own Baptiſm Lawful, yet being ſuch as have faith, this
Scripture ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently<pb n="130" facs="tcp:61819:80"/>Warrants us to receive
them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For the right underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this Text, Two
things ought to be conſidered, which if well weighed may give a clear
An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this Scripture Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 
<list>
                  <item>1. What Weakneſs this is, which the Apoſtle here
intends.</item>
                  <item>2. What is to be underſtood by Receiving ſuch.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The weakneſs ſpoken of in the Text, hath Relation only
to thoſe miſtakes that did attend ſome of them touching a liberty of
eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or not eating Meats, or the keeping or not keeping of days which were
things in themſelves of an indifferent Nature, the doing or not doing of
which, was not Sin, as the Apoſtle in that Chapter plainly ſhews; and hath
no Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Order of Worſhip pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by Chriſt, much leſs
to the Practice or not Practice of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,<pb n="131" facs="tcp:61819:80"/>for then
the meaning of the Apoſtle ſhould be, if they did practice, or not
practice, it was all one, there was no Sin in the matter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Receiving here cannot be meant to receive into the
Church as Members, Becauſe the Apoſtle Writes this Epiſtle to the Church,
and theſe weak Members as a part of that Church; but the Receiving here
intended is into the Affections of each other; that the differences that were
amongſt them ſhould not hinder the Law of Love, which they, and every
Chriſtian ought to cheriſh and Exerciſe towards each other, let their
differences be of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they will: That this muſt be the Senſe of
the Apoſtle, the clear Scope of the whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter makes evident. But to
bring this Text to prove a Lawfulneſs of receiving any that are Chriſtians
although never ſo ignorant of the<pb n="132" facs="tcp:61819:81"/>Ordinances, and
Inſtituted Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Chriſt, and the order pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by him is to
wring Blood out of it, and not that precious Truth that is manifeſted by
it.</p>
            <p>Object. 4. <hi>Whereas ſome infer from</hi> 1 Cor. 12.13. By one
Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit we are all Baptized into one Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, whether Jews or Gentiles, Bond or
Free, and have been all made to Drink into one Spirit, <hi>&amp;c. That
Baptiſm is the Inchurching Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, the concluſion is imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, for
not Water Baptiſm, but the Baptiſm of the Spirit is there meant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That Baptiſm was of ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and
Univerſal uſe to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>churching of all ſorts Ranks and Degrees, is
fairly deduced from this Text, however excepted againſt; and that none were
Inchurched without it, unleſs any man can find or name ſome perſons that 
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:61819:81"/>were neither <hi>Jews</hi> nor <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Bond nor
Free, which denotes plainly, that all ſorts were receiv'd by Baptiſm: the
<hi>Jews</hi> though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Circumciſed, yet were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; the
<hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſome times a People a far off were upon their believing by
Baptiſm received. If free, as Maſters, yet not admitted without it; If
Bond, as Servants, yet by this Ordinance they were made equally of the ſame
Church Priviledge by Baptiſm, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27,28.</p>
            <p>And that Water Baptiſm is here meant is the Judgment of the moſt
Learned Expoſitors: and the next words do make it Appear, <hi>We have been
all made to Drink into one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> By being baptized into one body and
made to Drink into one Spirit. The Apoſtle ſhews the Communion which
Believers have with the Holy Spirit in the Two Ordinances, <hi>Baptiſm</hi>
and the <hi>Lords Supper.</hi> For what elſe can<pb n="134" facs="tcp:61819:82"/>be
intended by Drinking into one Spirit, but the Saints Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Spirit,
in, and by the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>[Drinking]</hi> by a <hi>Synecdoche</hi> being put
both for Eating and Drinking: And if ſo, why muſt we not as well
underſtand the Firſt Ordinance in its proper Senſe for Water Baptiſm in
the former part, as the Later Ordinance, the Supper in the firſt part of the
Text.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Baptiſm of the Spirit had been meant, then the
being Baptiſed into one Body, and Drinking into one Spirit, muſt be one and
the ſame thing, but ſurely Baptiſing and Drinking are no more the ſame,
than the Body and the Spirit are the ſame, into which they are ſaid
reſpectively to be Baptiſed, and to Drink. But it is clear the Apoſtle
hereby intends to mind thoſe <hi>Corinthians,</hi> how that by means of the
ſame Spirit working upon all their Hearts, they became Members of the ſame 
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:61819:82"/>Body by Baptiſm, and that being of the Body, they came
to have Communion in Spirit, or with the Spirit in the Supper.</p>
            <p>It cannot be the Baptiſm of the Spirit, becauſe the Spirit is
here ſet forth by the Apoſtle, as the Agent or working Cauſe, and
Baptiſm as the Effect; and it is ridiculous to make both Cauſe and Effect
the ſame thing. It is true the Scripture ſpeaks elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where of a being
Baptiſed with the Spirit, but when it doth ſo, it ſtill declares either
Jeſus Chriſt, or God the Father as the Agent of Baptiſing with the
Spirit, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver as making the Spirit both the Subject Matter wherewith, and
the Agent whereby, men are Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in the ſame Baptiſm, ſee
<hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.8. <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.16. and 24.49.
<hi>Act.</hi> 11.4,5,16.</p>
            <p>We find in Scripture that when God chargeth men for ſin, he tells
them, <hi>They did that which he<pb n="136" facs="tcp:61819:83"/>commanded not, neither did
it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in his heart.</hi> Now that this was the Order of Adminiſtration
with reſpect to theſe Ordinances, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. To Teach, then
Baptiſe, and then Admit to Church-Communion, is elſe where fully Evidenc'd
from Precept and Example, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.41.
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> And if that be the ſtated Method of God, and the Univerſal
Practiſe of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, we may Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally infer that the
contrary Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe is a Deviation from the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Rule, and a thing which
God Commanded not.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle according to the Rule of Chriſt, firſt at
<hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> to put this Commiſſion in Execution, <hi>Luk.</hi>
24.47. And did Act according to it, and certainly their punctual Conformity to
it, ought to be taken by us as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of this grand Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and
their Example a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Pattern for ſucceeding Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, 
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:61819:83"/>unleſs we will ſuppoſe them to depart from it as
ſoon as they began to Act in purſuance of it, which ſuppoſition
includes a very ſtrange Uncharitableneſs, and a very unbecoming Opinion of
theſe Holy men. For nothing can be more plain than that Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to the
Church (or Church-Fellowſhip) followed after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and did not go
before it: and why men now find a greater good in their own way than in his, is
not to be eaſily reſolved. Baptiſm in thoſe days did certainly precede
Church-Enjoyments, for it was eſteem'd (as it ſtill ought to be) a means of
implanting men into Chriſt, or the Body of Chriſt the Church, <hi>Gal.</hi>
3.27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. Now let it be conſidered what a Planting together
imports; It muſt be certainly the firſt putting of Chriſtians together,
in order to their Growing together in Chriſt, and yet all this was done 
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:61819:84"/>by Baptiſm: and may we not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Trees to grow
together be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are Planted together, as this Spiritual Plantation of
Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the Church, or Society of Chriſtians, who were, and
ſhould ſtill be Planted together by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, not into this or that
parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church; but into that one Church of Chriſt, which is
diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted into ſeveral parts and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Societies. Hence Baptiſm
is called one of the Principles or begining Doctrines of Chriſt, and part of
the Foundation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1,2. Now there is no Houſe can ſtand
without its Principle, or can be Erected without a Foundation. See 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. Where we have an account of all being Baptiſed into one
Body, whether Jews or Gentiles, Bond or Free, which comprehended all Ranks and
De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Chriſtians, as is elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where demonſtrated.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:61819:84"/>Obj. 5. <hi>The Phraſe,</hi> Rom. 6.3. and
Gal. 3.27. [As many] of you as have been Baptiſed into Chriſt, &amp;c.
<hi>implies that all that were in thoſe Churches of</hi> Rome <hi>and</hi>
Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia <hi>were not Baptiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If we conſult the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture with the Coherence,
it will appear how weak this Objection is.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For that <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3. Let it be conſidered to whom
the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle writes: Is it not to the whole Church, and every individual of
them? In verſe 1, 2. When he ſays, <hi>What ſhall we ſay then? Shall we
continue in ſin, that Grace may abound? God forbid. How ſhall we that are
dead to ſin, live any longer therein? ?</hi> If theſe words in the firſt
and ſecond Verſe reſpect the whole Church, as they muſt be ſuppoſed
to do, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we will conclude that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <pb n="140" facs="tcp:61819:85"/>did
grant a liberty to ſome of the Church to continue in ſin, and live therein,
then theſe words, <hi>Know ye not that as many of us as were Baptiſed into
Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. Are Interrogatively propounded not only to the
ſame perſons, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom the former words relate, but alſo as an Argument
or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why none of them ſhould live any longer in ſin, which is the
thing from which he was a diſſuad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not only ſome of them, but even all
of them in the foregoing verſes, and which he improves in an Argumentative
way through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the greateſt part of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and it would not befit the
Reaſon of any ordinary man, much leſs of a Great Apoſtle to make choice a
Reaſon or Motive to infore his Exhortation or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, which is of
leſs extent in the tendency and concernment of it, then are the perſons
whom he doth Exhort or Dehort. Which <pb n="141" facs="tcp:61819:85"/>yet is a piece of
weakneſs, of which we muſt ſuppoſe this Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to be guilty,
unleſs you do conclude that all thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> were
diſſuaded from continuing any longer in ſin upon this ground, becauſe
they had been all Baptiſed into the Death of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> a
Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to his Death, as well as a belief of it. To conclude, If the whole
Church had not been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Motive, the whole Church could not be
preſſed by it as here you ſee they are.</p>
            <p>As for the other Text,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.26,27.</note>
               <hi>Gal</hi> 3.26. the Apoſtle had aſſured them, <hi>viz.</hi> them to
whom he now writes, <hi>To be all the children of God by Faith in Chriſt
Jeſus,</hi> that is they were lookt upon as children of God by their
confeſſing and owning of Jeſus Chriſt, of which he gives this account,
<hi>verſe</hi> 27. Becauſe they had put on Chriſt in Baptiſm <hi>You
are all the children of God by<pb n="142" facs="tcp:61819:86"/>Faith in Chriſt Jeſus,
for, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, as many of you, as have been Baptiſed into Chriſt, have
put on Chriſt:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, if the Owning and Profeſſing
Chriſt does denominate men to be the Children of God, now under the Goſpel,
as indeed it does, then ye are all the Children of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by being
Baptiſed into Chriſt, ye have all of you put him on, that is, ſo to
appear with him, wherever ye become, as you do appear with the Clothes you
wear. But now moſt certain it is, they could not all of them have been
denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated the Children of God by Faith in Chriſt, upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their
being Baptiſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt (which yet we ſee they are) unleſs they had
been all of them Baptiſed into Chriſt indeed.</p>
            <p>Beſides in what hath been ſaid already it does not appear that 
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:61819:86"/>any in the Apoſtles days were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>churched without
Baptiſm. And for any to aſſert that ſome, not all, were Baptiſed, is
to affirm what is void of Scripture, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and Common Senſe. As for any
countenance in Scripture, there is none—And it has as little in Reaſon:
for if it ſhould be true, it will follow that this Great Ordinance was a duty
to ſome on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not to all, and the Reaſon why it ſhould be ſo, will
be very difficult to aſſign, was it becauſe it was commanded to ſome
only, and not others? If ſo, let them be inſtanced by ſome kind of
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, who were obliged to the Practiſe, and who not: was it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
ſome only had need of it, and others not? or becauſe thoſe glorious
myſteries repreſented by it, were uſeleſs to ſome, and not to all? Or
what other Reaſon was it? If none can be aſſigned, then we may ſafely
conclude that all<pb n="144" facs="tcp:61819:87"/>Church-Members were then Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed; and
ought to be ſo ſtill.</p>
            <p>It is confeſſed that ſometimes the Phraſe <hi>[As many]</hi>
has not the ſame Latitude of ſignification as the Phraſe <hi>[All
men]</hi> which includes every Individual, the term <hi>[As many]</hi> being
reſtrained to matter going before being then Partitive: But here it has
Relation to the whole ſcope of the Text, and muſt therefore intend all, or
all of that Church to whom he wrote, to confirm which Interpretation we find
other Texts <hi>[As many]</hi> muſt of neceſſity be ſo underſtood as
1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Let as many ſervants as are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> under the Yoke,
count their own Maſters worthy of all Honour:</hi> doth he thereby
ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or may it be implyed that there were ſome ſervants who were
not under the Yoke, or that there were ſome Servants who were not to count
their Maſters worthy of all Honour? But<pb n="145" facs="tcp:61819:87"/>which muſt be
ſuppoſed notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, if this form or manner of ſpeaking <hi>(as
many as)</hi> be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to be underſtood to intend the dividing of the
intire Number of Perſons ſpoken unto; which yet to ſuppoſe muſt needs
be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry abſurd.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>And if it be ſaid, That this Exhortation, let as many
Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants as</hi> &amp;c. <hi>doth intentionally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſo many Believing
Servants as were under to Yoke; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in reſpect of other
Believers it is partitive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If that be granted there will be more gained than
other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: for then it may well be ſaid, that thoſe Texts, <hi>Rom.</hi>
6.3. <hi>Gall.</hi> 3.27. Intentionally, only reſpected thoſe at
<hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Gallatia,</hi> who did Believe, and were Baptized; and
therefore is partitive in reſpect of others, the Inhabitants of thoſe 
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:61819:88"/>places, dividing thoſe of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, from others
dwelling in the ſame places, who were not of thoſe Churches.</p>
            <p>Object. 6. <hi>If it be Objected from</hi> Act. 9.26. <hi>That we
find not there, when</hi> Paul <hi>was preſented to the Church at</hi>
Jeruſalem, <hi>and Aſſayed to joyn himſelf to the Diſciples, that the
Church made any inquiry whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was Baptized or no, in order to his
Reception amongſt them; or that</hi> Barnabas <hi>in giving ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
to the Apoſtles and the Church concerning his meetneſs to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into
Communion with them, ſo much as mentions his being Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, but only
declareth unto them, how he had ſeen the Lord in the way, and that he had
ſpoken to him, and how he had Preached boldly at</hi> Damaſcus <hi>in the
Name of Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is no good Reaſon can be given, or to
ſuppoſe that<pb n="147" facs="tcp:61819:88"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> was admitted to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
with the Church, until the Church had knowledg either from himſelf,
<hi>Barnabus,</hi> or ſome other, of his having obey'd the Goſpel in
Embracing the firſt Principles of it; of which Baptiſm is one,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. For how ſhould they know him to be a Diſciple of
Chriſt and ſo meet for Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them, but by knowing that he had at
leaſt done the firſt things of a Diſciple, of which we find all along the
Hiſtory of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, a <hi>Being Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized,</hi>
to be one, and doubtleſs leſs ſatisfaction would not have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them
concerning him, than would concerning another Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who had never
appeared in that height of oppoſition againſt them, as he had done.</p>
            <p>Again, when the Text tells us, That <hi>Barnabas</hi> declared unto
them, how he had ſeen the Lord in the way, and had ſpoken to him; can 
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:61819:89"/>it be thought he could ſay leſs then what it was, that
the Lord had ſpoke to him? And if ſo, then how can it be thought but that
the Relation of his being Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized muſt needs come in at his Report to them?
inaſmuch as that Direction which the Lord gave <hi>Paul,</hi> about his going
into a <hi>Straight ſtreet</hi> in order to his fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Information,
touching the Will of the Lord concerning him, to Rehearſe the Carriage of
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias</hi> towards <hi>Saul;</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently his baptizing of
him: unleſs it ſhould be ſuppoſed, that <hi>Barnabas</hi> made a broken
and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Relation of the Lords deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him, which we cannot do
without Judging <hi>Barnabas</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther weak or careleſs in that great
buſineſs: For it cannot be thought that <hi>Barnabas</hi> uſed no more
words in this Relation then what are here Recorded by <hi>Luke;</hi> ſince we
have frequently, if not for the moſt<pb n="149" facs="tcp:61819:89"/>part; but the brief
Heads of things. Recorded that were done, and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Chriſt, the
Apoſtles, and other Diſciples, <hi>John</hi> 21.25. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.40.</p>
            <p>And we find <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf in making the Relation of that
great Providence of the Lord towards him in his Converſion, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
mention his Baptiſm, <hi>Act.</hi> 22.5, to 16. and that which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
of him to be found in the Practice of, before he ſhould go forth in the
performance of that great Work he was Called unto, namely, to Preach the
Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Object. 7. <hi>It is Objected, that this was in the Infancy of the
Church, and is no binding Rule to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If that be no Rule to us, let it be ſhown where
there is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Rule? beſides do not all men of any underſtanding know,
that this is the great Argument<pb n="150" facs="tcp:61819:90"/>brought to Countenance
Infant Baptiſm: And is not this the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence by which all thoſe
Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Men in the Worſhip of God are brought in? How greatly is that
place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. abus'd and miſtaken? <hi>Let all things be done
decently and in Order.</hi> From whence men take upon them to preſcribe what
they pleaſe, and call it Order, impoſing the ſame upon Mens
Conſciences, whereas Order and Decency there, muſt reſpect that Order
which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had preſcribed in the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Verſes, wherein is
ſhewn, what Order ought to be uſed in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of thoſe ſeveral
Gifts which God hath given to that Church, in the Exerciſe whereof the Church
might receive Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They eſpecially that are afraid to comply with
the Inventions of men in the Worſhip of God in ſome things, ſhould above
all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be careful of bringing in any<pb n="151" facs="tcp:61819:90"/>Inventions of
their own in other things, leſt while they build again themſelves the
things they De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy in others; they make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Tranſgreſſors,
and give that advantage to others they would not willingly do.</p>
            <p>Object. 8. <hi>A main thing built upon, is, that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with
Chriſt gives a Right to all the Ordinances of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is readily granted, that Union with Chriſt,
ſignifyed by a viſible Profeſſion of Faith gives a man Right to
Baptiſm, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this Union and being bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, they have a Right to
Church Fellowſhip, and the <hi>Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> &amp;c. but that by vertue
of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Chriſt they have a right to the Lords Supper; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly
to partake of the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are Baptized is Deny'd from the Reaſons
already given,<pb n="152" facs="tcp:61819:91"/>nor can it any where be proved.</p>
            <p>This may be plainly illuſtrated by this ſimilitude. A Child, by
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Eldeſt Son of his Father, has a Right to his Fathers Eſtate as
Heir thereof, as ſoon as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is dead, but yet for the actual
Poſſeſſion thereof, there is required his coming to Age, till which
time he cannot Poſſeſs that Right; the Law requiring this as the Order by
which he is to come to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment thereof. So though Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Chriſt
gives a man a Right to all the Ordinances of Chriſt, yet are they to be
enjoyed in that Order which the Law pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth.</p>
            <p>Obj. 9. <hi>This is a Dividing Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, and 'tis very
cenſorious to judge none fit for Communion in a Church, but ſuch as are
Baptiſed thereby, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtianing all other Perſons that are of another
mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:61819:91"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is no other Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
but what the Scripture doth every where juſtifie, as hath been largely proved
before. And this Objection is rather chargeable on the contrary Opinion, as
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which divides the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from its proper uſe and end by
putting it out of its place, where God in his Word hath ſet it. There being
no Diviſion made by Principle, but what is made by the ignorance of the
perſons that Oppoſe it about the Rule and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by which Chriſtians
ought to walk; or by their wilful neglect of that which is required by the
Lord, of thoſe that deſire Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Church. For if the Lord of
the Family pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe an Order by which it ſhould be Governed, can it be
reaſonable that his Rule ſhould be broken for the ſake of the Servants
Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or wilfulneſs?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:61819:92"/>2. We cenſure none ſo rigidly as to
take upon us to Unchriſtian or Unchurch them; all that we do is (in
diſcharge of our Duty to God, and Faithfulneſs in our pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) to labour to
keep the Lords Ordinances in that Purity and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sacred Records
teſtifie they were left in, and in a Spirit of Love and Meekneſs to
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend earneſtly for the Faith once delivered to the Saints;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.2. Jude 3.</note> which we conceive to be a Duty
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned upon all Chriſtians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. 10. <hi>It hath been Objected from</hi> Eph. 4.4,5,6. <hi>Where
under the ſeveral Heads there is in the fourth Head one Baptiſm. Now
ſaith the Objector if we believe the other ſix things there mentioned,</hi>
viz. <hi>One Body, one Spirit, even as ye are called in one Hope of your
Calling, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of all,</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>and are not found in the Practiſe of the <pb n="155" facs="tcp:61819:92"/>fourth Head,</hi> viz. <hi>one Baptiſm; what Reaſon is there that
we ſhould be deprived of Communion in the Lords Supper, for either the
neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of it, and not ſeeing we are bound to Practiſe it?</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It doth appear from the Text that this is a Golden
Chain linked together by the Spirit of God himſelf, the taking of one of
which Links away may weaken the whole: and if the Wiſdom of the Spirit hath
linked or joyned them together, it ſeems to be great preſumption in any to
put them a ſunder. Therefore let it be noted that the Apoſtle
<hi>verſe</hi> 3. Exhorts the Church to keep the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in
the bond of Peace.</hi> In the 4, 5, 6. verſes he ſhews, wherein the Unity
of the Spirit which is to be kept conſiſts, by giving a Character of the
True Apoſtolick Religion, epitomized under ſeven Heads. 
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:61819:93"/> 
               <list>
                  <item>1. One God and Father of all, who is above all, and in us
all.</item>
                  <item>2. One Lord the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the man Chriſt
Jeſus; by whom, and for whom are all things, the great Mediator betwixt God
and Man.</item>
                  <item>3. One Faith, Believing in this one God, and this one Lord
Jeſus the one Mediator.</item>
                  <item>4. One Baptiſm, which in all the three Editions thereof
hath ſignified a Profeſſion and Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to this one God, and one
Mediator by the Profeſſion of the one Faith.</item>
                  <item>5. One Spirit proceeding from the Father and the Son, the
great Teacher and Inſtructor of this one Body into a further Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with
the Father and the Son.</item>
                  <item>6. One Body, whereof all the Baptiſed are profeſſed
Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and whereto they are<pb n="157" facs="tcp:61819:93"/>compleatly United by that
one Spirit.</item>
                  <item>7. One hope of their Calling, in believing the Reſurrection
of the Body, and Eternal Life, which God hath promiſed to all thoſe that
obey him.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>From this we may with much Aſſurance infer, that we are under an
indiſpenſable Obligation to be found in the Practice of this one Baptiſm,
which holds forth our Intereſt in, and Profeſſion of this one God and
Father, one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and one Spirit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whoſe Name we are
Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be Baptiſed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The
Objector ſuppoſes the bare Belief (without the viſible Profeſſion) of
Baptiſm, is enough; which indeed is not ſo: becauſe the Nature and
Conſtitution of this Ordinance is purely Practical by vertue of a poſitive
Precept, and no pretence of a ſpeculative<pb n="158" facs="tcp:61819:94"/>Belief will
excuſe the neglect of it; any more than the neglect of an Exerciſe of Faith
reſpecting any other of the ſix points, which the Holy Spirit has joyned
with it.<note place="margin">The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients tell us the Form of Baptiſm when
they Expound, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5. <hi>One Law.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Whereas it may be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Queryed. Whether one
Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance gives a Right to the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is anſwered, no; For we have before proved
that all Ordinances are to be obſerved in that Order which the Appointer of
them hath preſcribed; from which we ought not to vary. For as Circumciſion
was the firſt Ordinance to be Adminiſtred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they might be partakers
of the Paſſeover although it gave not a Right to the Paſſeover, yet
might not any partake of it (before they were Circumciſed) without ſin: So
alſo in the New Teſtament,<pb n="159" facs="tcp:61819:94"/>Baptiſm is the firſt
Ordinance to be Adminiſtred by the direction and appointment of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
which, the Supper of the Lord may not be received without Sin. All that is
pleaded for by this, is the <hi>Orderly</hi> obſervation of the New
Teſtament Ordinances.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But why ſhould any be debar'd the enjoyment of
thoſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances they have light into, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they want light in
others?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It deſerves to be ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſidered,
whether the neglect of the Ordinance of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm doth not more ariſe from
the want of a heart to obey God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, by reaſon of the contempt put upon
it, then for want of Light. Is any Ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt in the New
Teſtament more plain and clear than this? Are there not many more inſtances
in the New Teſtament for the Practiſe <pb n="160" facs="tcp:61819:95"/>of this then the
Lords Supper? For beſides the Inſtitution of it by Jeſus Chriſt,
inſtanced by the ſeveral Evangeliſts, it is but four times mentioned,
<hi>viz. Act.</hi> 2.42. &amp; 20.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. &amp; 11.23.
Whereas we find beſides the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion given by Jeſus Chriſt,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. &amp;c. that 'tis again enjoyned, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38.
&amp; 8.38. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.48. &amp; 16.15.33. <hi>Act.</hi> 9.18.
<hi>Act.</hi> 18.8. &amp;c. Neither do we find any one Ordinance of the
Goſpel ſo much made uſe of by the Apoſtles to incite Chriſtians to
die to ſin, and live to Cod, as is largely demonſtrated in the foregoing
ſheets, to which we refer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. 11. <hi>And whereas it may be Objected that 'tis Love and not
Baptiſm, that diſcovers us to be Chriſts Diſciples;</hi> It is
anſwered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We do readily confeſs<pb n="161" facs="tcp:61819:95"/>that we
are commanded to put on love, <hi>Coll.</hi> 3.14. which is a great Character
of a Diſciple of Chriſt, and it is much to be Lamented, that there is ſo
little ſeen among Saints: Yet that cannot be called Love, which is
exerciſed in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Order preſcribed in the Word, by which
Ordinances ought to be Adminiſtred; For as Love is a grace of the Spirit of
Chriſt; ſo Ordinances are the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments of the ſame Spirit which
works Grace in the Hearts of Chriſtians; All true Goſpel Love being
Regulated by Goſpel-Rule; and as all men may know the Diſciples of Chriſt
by their Love one to another: ſo alſo, it is a Character given by the
ſame Lord, of being a Diſciple when this Love is manifeſt in keeping his
Commandements, <hi>John</hi> 14.15. <hi>If ye Love me keep my
Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> ver. 21. <hi>He that hath my Commandements, and keepeth
them,<pb n="130" facs="tcp:61819:96"/>he it is that loveth me, and he that loveth me,
ſhall be beloved of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and I will love him and will manifeſt my
ſelf to him.</hi> ver. 23. <hi>Jeſus anſwered and ſaid, If any man Love
me, he will keep my Words, and my Father will love him, and we will come unto
him, and make our aboad with him.</hi> ver. 24. <hi>He that loveth me not,
keepeth not my ſayings, and the Word which you hear is not mine, but the
Fathers which ſent me.</hi> Now of theſe Commandments this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of
Baptiſm is not the leaſt, and it ſeems to ſavour of little Love in them
that would have Men believe, it is advanced in them above their Brethren to
charge them with want of Love, as the only Reaſon why they cannot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
perſons to the Supper of the Lord, that never yet Received the Baptiſm of
Chriſt. Therefore,</p>
            <p>Here we can Appeal to the Searcher of Hearts, That the true Reaſon
is, becauſe we dare not<pb n="131" facs="tcp:61819:96"/>break that Rule and Order by
which we find the Primitive Saints walkt, and not want of Love to them. And the
Sence we have of the great Severity God hath ſhewed againſt thoſe that
have made the leaſt Breach upon that Order which he himſelf hath
preſcribed.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I leave to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Conſideration of thoſe
to whom this brief Eſſay may come, deſiring they may <hi>try all thing,
and hold faſt that which is Good.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
